<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An account of Mr. Firmin's religion, and of the present state of the Unitarian controversy</title>
            <author>Nye, Stephen, 1648?-1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 111 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52602</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N1502</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4610</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13081202</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13081202</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97237</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52602)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97237)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 747:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An account of Mr. Firmin's religion, and of the present state of the Unitarian controversy</title>
                  <author>Nye, Stephen, 1648?-1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>83 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Stephen Nye. Cf. McAlpin Coll.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Firmin, Thomas, 1632-1697.</term>
               <term>Unitarians --  England.</term>
               <term>Socinianism.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97237:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97237:1"/>
            <p>AN ACCOUNT OF <hi>Mr. Firmin's</hi> RELIGION; AND OF The Preſent State OF THE UNITARIAN CONTROVERSY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year 1698.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:97237:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:97237:2"/>
            <head>AN ACCOUNT OF <hi>Mr. Firmin's</hi> RELIGION.</head>
            <p>MR. <hi>Firmin</hi> was remarkable, above almoſt any private Man of this Nation and Age, for his care and agency on behalf of the Poor; and his zeal and activity for his way (or Sect) of Religion. I ſhall ſay nothing of the former; we have an account of his diligence, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods for the Poor, from ſome friends of his, that knew him longer, and with the neareſt intimacy. But concerning lib Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, I may claim to know as much of it, as any other. It was the ſame in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral with that of all Proteſtants, that is,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97237:3"/>the H. Bible; and the Apoſtles Creed, as the abridgment of the Chriſtian Faith con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd in that Book. But as for the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of Articles controverted, it was that which he and his party call <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian;</hi> but others <hi>Socinian.</hi> Mr. <hi>Firmin,</hi> and the Engliſh <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians,</hi> never were entirely in the ſentiments of <hi>F. Socinus; they embraced, the opinions of Mr.</hi> J. Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Bidle</hi> differ'd from <hi>Socinus,</hi> and the foreign <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians,</hi> as in ſome other points, ſo in that, he believed the H. Spirit is, tho' not <hi>God,</hi> yet a <hi>Perſon</hi> in the vulgar ſenſe of that word.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Firmn</hi> was a very diſcerning but not a learned Man. Some others of his party have all the qualities, for which the foreign <hi>Socinians</hi> have been ſo much eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; that is to ſay, beſides an acuteneſs and dexterity of Thought, they are excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently Learned, eſpecially in the ſacred Criticiſm. But that which, in my opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, moſt commends him and them, is the freedom and ſincerity, which they have all along practiſed, in judging of the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted Articles</hi> of Religion. They fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed indeed, an firſt, Mr. <hi>Bidle</hi> (as he eſpouſed the Tenets of <hi>Socinus</hi>) but ſo, that as ſoon as there appeared better light,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97237:3"/>(to uſe a Scripture Phraſe) <hi>they rejoyced in it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From the time that <hi>F. Socinus,</hi> and his Doctrines, began to be taken notice of; the Churches, of all denominations, were perſuaded, the difference between <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nianiſm,</hi> and the doctrin of the <hi>Catholic Church,</hi> was Real, Great, and even Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reconcilable. Many learned Men have thought, ſome ſuch degree of accord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Church, and other Diſſenters, might be deviſed, that they might bear with one another, and hold occaſional Communion: But <hi>Socinianiſm</hi> was ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be a departure from the Churches Doctrin, ſo <hi>far,</hi> and in ſo <hi>many</hi> points, that no Coalition, in Communion, much leſs in Doctrine, might ever be hoped. And of this mind were the Engliſh <hi>Socini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> as well as the Foreign; and both of them no leſs earneſtly than the Church. But, as I ſaid, the Engliſh <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> (or <hi>Socinians</hi>) being Men of ingenuous and free Minds and Principles; and therefore al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ready to entertain farther light: after 8 or 9 years late conteſt, in print, with the principal Divines of this Nation, they have been ſo dextrous and happy, that, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of farther embroiling the points in queſtion, which is the uſual effect of the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97237:4"/>Paper-war, they ſeem to have accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dated whatſoever differences depending between the Church and them.</p>
            <p>A greater Service, or any equal to it, was perhaps never done, to the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic Church. For as on the one ſide the <hi>Socinians.</hi> being ſo much the Jeſſer Party, flood expoſed to all the poenal Laws in any Nation, that had ever been enacted againſt any fort of Heretics: So the Church was more dangerouſly threatned, by this <hi>Cloud, of the bigneſs of a man's hand,</hi> than by all other Diſſenters, or Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers whatſoever. The opinions of the <hi>Socinians,</hi> had that appearance of <hi>Reaſon;</hi> ſuch an agreement with all the yielded Principles of <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> whether Natural or Metaphyſied: that if they had been foſtered by the helps, under the cover and ſhelter of which, other denominations of Religion have made ſhift to ſubſiſt; <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nianiſm</hi> would have flouriſht and ſpread like that Tree in the Prophet <hi>Daniel; the hight whereof reached to Heaven, and the ſight thereof to the ends of all the Earth.</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sects, by the favour of Princes, or the quality of the times, have obtained an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption, from Mulcts, and Penalties of the Laws: and thus, their courſe not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing impeded by any dams or banks; they
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97237:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>have over-ſpread ſometimes conſiderable parts of particular Countries. If <hi>Socini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aniſm</hi> had any where enjoyed thoſe <hi>Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon-days,</hi> its ſudden, irreſiſtible Progreſs would have been (that I may again bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row one of the ſacred Compariſons) as <hi>Lightning, that ruſheth out of the Eaſt, and ſhineth even to the Weſt.</hi> Alas, on equal Ground, and with equal Circumſtances, the combat between (unintelligible) <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery,</hi> and (clear) <hi>Reaſon;</hi> between (ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) Contradictions, Abſurdities and <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibilities,</hi> and (a rational, obvious, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable) <hi>Faith,</hi> would ſoon have been ended.</p>
            <p>But 'tis better ended: The Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence and Goodneſs, in mercy to both Parties, has granted a Peace, inſtead of a Victory. It has pleaſed God to favor the ſuffering ſide with an unexpected Light; he has ſhown 'em what may ſeem incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that their Oppoſers <hi>think,</hi> as they (the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi>) <hi>ſpeak;</hi> that their differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is not in the ideas or notions, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the terms or words. To manifeſt this, Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> cauſed the following <hi>Scheme of Agreement,</hi> offer'd to him by a Perſon long converſant in theſe queſtions, to be conſidered by ſome of the principal <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> in <hi>England:</hi> And being ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97237:5"/>by him and them, it was publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about a year ſince.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Scheme of Agreement.</head>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> after having publiſhed di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers good Books, and one that may deſerve the epithet of Excellent, <hi>his Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Exiſtence and Providence of God,</hi> found an inclination in himſelf, that he could not (it ſhould ſeem) reſiſt of contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a New Religion, or rather Impiety; and of imputing it <hi>to the Socinians.</hi> By whom he means (it appears) the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thoſe in <hi>England,</hi> who call themſelves <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians,</hi> never were entirely in the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents of <hi>Socinus,</hi> or the <hi>Socinians.</hi> Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, as our Oppoſers have pleas'd themſelves in calling us <hi>Socinians,</hi> we have not always declined the name; becauſe in interpreting many texts of Scripture, we cannot but approve and follow the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thoſe Writers; who are confeſſed by all to be excellent Critics, and very Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious. As particularly, and chiefly, <hi>H. Grotius,</hi> who, it muſt be granted, was <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinian</hi> all over: And <hi>D. Eraſmus,</hi> who, tho' he lived considerably before <hi>Socinus,</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:97237:5"/>commonly interprets that way; and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is charged, by Card. <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> as a downright <hi>Arian. Non poterat,</hi> ſays the Cardinal, <hi>Arianam cauſam manifeſtiùs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnare.</hi> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>Eraſmus</hi> could not more open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſpouſe the <hi>Arian</hi> Cauſe, than he has done; in his Notes on the Fathers, and on the principal Texts of H. Scripture. <bibl>
                        <hi>Praef. ad libros</hi> 5. <hi>de Chriſto.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q> But tho, as I ſaid, we are not <hi>Socinians,</hi> nor yet <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians;</hi> ſeeing Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> has contrived a Creed for us, under the name of <hi>Socinians,</hi> I will anſwer both directly and ſincerely concerning the ſeveral Articles of the Creed, which he ſaith is ours.</p>
               <p>As to the References unto places in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Authors, where Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> would have it thought, the Articles of that Creed are affirmed: I have examined ſome of his principal References, and can ſay of 'em, they are either Perverſions, or downright Falſifications, of what the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors referred to did intend. Dr. <hi>Wallis,</hi> whoſe diſhoneſt Quotations out of the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians,</hi> have been deteſted by every body, is hardly more blamable in that kind than Mr. <hi>Edwards;</hi> ſaving that the Doctor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as one rightly tells him, ſomewhat <hi>more</hi> than a <hi>Socinian,</hi> did but foul his own Neſt by his Forgeries: but we cannot cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97237:6"/>ſay what is the opinion of Mr. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> in the great Article, in queſtion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us.</p>
               <p>But come we to the Creed, which he ſays is ours: as I promis'd, I will anſwer to every Article of it, ſincerely and direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="article">
               <p n="1">I. <hi>I believe, concerning the Scriptures, that there are Errors, Miſtakes, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions in ſome places of it: That the Authority of ſome whole books of it is queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable; yea, that the whole Bible has been tamper'd with, and may be ſuſpected to be corrupted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That <hi>there are Errors, Miſtakes, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions in the H. Bible,</hi> was never ſaid by any perſon, pretending to be a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an: if by the Bible, you mean <hi>the Bible, as it came out of the hands of the inſpired Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of it.</hi> As on the other ſide, that there are Errors, Miſtakes, or Contradictions in the vulgar Copies of the Bible, uſed by the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> (for inſtance) or the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Church, was never queſtioned by any learned Man, of whatſoever Sect or way: and leaſt of all can Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> queſtion it. He has publiſhed a book concerning <hi>the Excellence and Perfection of</hi> H. Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97237:6"/>in which book, he finds great fault with our Engliſh Bible. He ſaith, in the Title of his 13th chapter; <q>It is <hi>faulty,</hi> and <hi>defective,</hi> in many places of the Old and New Teſtaments; and I offer all along in this chapter particular <hi>Emen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations,</hi> in order to render it more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act and compleat.</q>
               </p>
               <p>As to the <hi>Hebrew</hi> and <hi>Greek</hi> copies of the Bible; 'tis well known, ſome are more perfect, and ſome leſs: They differ very much; for in the Old Teſtament, the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Critics have noted 800 various rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings; in the New there are many more. Mr. <hi>Gregory</hi> of <hi>Oxford,</hi> ſo much eſteemed, and even venerated, for his admirable Learning, ſays hereupon; and ſays it, <hi>cum Licentiâ Superiorum:</hi> 
                  <q>There is no book in the World, that has ſuffer'd ſo much, by the hand of Time, as the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. <bibl>
                        <hi>Pref.</hi> p. 4.</bibl>
                  </q> He judged, and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed truly, that tho' the firſt Authors of the Bible were <hi>Divinely Inſtructed Men;</hi> yet the Copiers, Printers, and Publiſhers, in following Ages, were all of them <hi>Fallible</hi> Men, and ſome of them ill-deſigning Men. He knew that all the Church Hiſtorians, and Critics, have confeſſed, or rather have <hi>warned</hi> us, that ſome copies of the Bible, have been very much vitiated by the hands
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97237:7"/>as well of the Orthodox, as of Heretics: and that 'tis matter of great difficulty, at this diſtance of time from the Apoſtolic Age, to aſſertain the true reading of H. Scripture, in <hi>all</hi> places of it.</p>
               <p>Yet we do not ſay hereupon, as Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> charges us, that the Bible, much leſs the <hi>whole</hi> Bible, is corrupted. For as to the faulty readings in the common Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of ſome Churches, and in ſome Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript Copies; the Providence of God has ſo watched over this ſacred Book, that we know (what by information of the anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>Church-Hiſtorians,</hi> and the writings of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> what by the <hi>early Tranſlations</hi> of the Bible into <hi>Greek, Latin,</hi> and <hi>Syriac,</hi> and the <hi>concurrent</hi> Teſtimony of the more <hi>antient Manuſcript copies</hi>) both who they were that introduced the <hi>corrupt</hi> readings, and what is the <hi>true</hi> Reading in all <hi>Texts of weight and conſequence.</hi> In ſhort, as to this matter, we agree with the Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tics of other Sects and Denominations; that tho' ill Men have often attempted, they could never effect the corruption of H. Scripture: the antient <hi>Manuſcripts,</hi> the firſt <hi>Tranſlations,</hi> the <hi>Fathers,</hi> and <hi>Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> of the Church, are ſufficient direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, concerning the authentic and genu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine Reading of doubtful places of H. Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:97237:7"/>
               <p>Farther, whereas Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> would intimate, that we reject divers Books of H. Scripture: On the contrary we receive into our Canon all thoſe Books of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that are received or owned by the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and we reject the Books rejected by the Church of <hi>England.</hi> We know well that ſome Books and parts of Books, reckoned to be wrote by the Apoſtles or Apoſtolical Men, were que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned, nay were refuſed by ſome of the Antients; but we concur with the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>preſent</hi> Catholic Church con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them, for the reaſons given by the Catholic Church, and which I mention in the Reply to my Lord the Bp. of <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> would have truly repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented the opinion of the <hi>Socinians</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scriptures, he knew where to find it, and ſo expreſſed as would have ſatisfied every body. He knows that in the <hi>Brief Notes on the Creed of</hi> Athanaſius, they have declared what is their ſenſe in very unexceptionable words: <q>
                     <hi>The Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> ſay they, <hi>are a</hi> divine, <hi>an</hi> infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, <hi>and</hi> compleat <hi>Rule, both of Faith and Manners.</hi> 
                     <bibl>Br. Notes, <hi>p.</hi> 1.</bibl>
                  </q> The Church neither requires nor deſires that they ſhould ſay more.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="article">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:97237:8"/>
               <p n="2">II. <hi>I believe concerning God, That he is not a Spirit, properly ſpeaking; but a ſort of</hi> Body, <hi>ſuch as Air or</hi> Aether <hi>is. That he is not immenſe, infinite, or every where preſent, but confined to certain places. That he hath no knowledg of ſuch future Events, as depend on the</hi> Free Will <hi>of Man: and That it is impoſſible ſuch things ſhould be foreſeen by him. That there is</hi> a Succeſſion <hi>in God's eternal duration, as well as in time, which is the meaſure of the duration that belong</hi> to finite Beings.</p>
               <p>That Almighty God is <hi>Incorporeal, Omnipreſent</hi> and <hi>Omniſcient,</hi> has not only been confeſſed, but proved by the Unita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians of this Nation in divers of their late Prints. As to the other, that all Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, that of God as well as of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, conſiſts <hi>in a Succeſſion,</hi> is affirmed by ſome Learned Men of all Perſwaſions and Ways, as well as by the Unitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. It ſhould ſeem Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> holds, that God poſſeſſes eternal Lite <hi>all at once:</hi> that to God, Eternity is one ſtanding <hi>permanent Moment.</hi> St. <hi>John</hi> is of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mind, for he deſcribes the duration of God by <hi>a Succeſſion;</hi> by <hi>was, is,</hi> and <hi>is to come.</hi> 
                  <q>Grace be to you, and Peace, <hi>ſays he,</hi> from him which <hi>is, was,</hi> and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97237:8"/>
                     <hi>is to come,</hi> 
                     <bibl>Rev. 1.4.</bibl>
                  </q> 'Tis undeniable by any, but affected Wranglers, that here the duration of God, his continuance in being, is diſtinguiſhed by <hi>the threefold Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion</hi> (<hi>was, is,</hi> and <hi>ſhall be</hi>) which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all Beings. Eternal life poſſeſſed <hi>all at once,</hi> is one of the monſtrous Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxes which our Oppoſers maintain; for all that I can ſee, meerly from a ſpirit of contradiction; for it has no manner of ground, either in Reaſon or Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. I deſire to know of 'em how the duration of God, is the leſs perfect; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe 'tis ſaid to conſiſt in <hi>a Succeſſion,</hi> or what is the ſame, to be diſtinguiſhed by <hi>was, is,</hi> and <hi>ſhall be:</hi> ſeeing 'tis confeſſed on all hands, that he carrieth all Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons into every Succeſſion of his Duration.</p>
               <p>But is it not a Scandal that ſome Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians of foreign Parts, have denied the Spirituality or Incorporeity of God; his Omnipreſence and Omniſcience: ſaying and contending for it, that he is <hi>a Body,</hi> with ſuch Configuration of Parts as <hi>Men</hi> have; conſequently that he is in Heaven, inſpecting indeed and governing all things, but by the miniſtry of the ſeveral Orders of Angels; and that he doth not foreſee contingent Events, but only ſuch Events as are <hi>neceſſarily</hi> (not arbitrarily) produced by
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97237:9"/>their Cauſes? Doubtleſs; but no more a ſcandal to the Unitarians, than to their Oppoſers: for they are <hi>Errors</hi> which ſome of the <hi>Fathers</hi> (even the moſt: antient, learned and pious of 'em) have defended as Truths. Nay it ſhould ſeem, they were ſome time the prevaling Opinions in ſome places: namely, when the Anthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pomorphite Doctrine was ſo zealouſly eſpouſed; that the <hi>Hermits</hi> and <hi>Ceno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bites</hi> would not indure their Biſhops, if they but ſuſpected 'em of <hi>Origen</hi>'s Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, that God is <hi>a Spirit, without Parts or Paſſions.</hi> And in denying the Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuality and Omnipreſence of God, they muſt needs be underſtood not to believe his (certain and abſolute) Preſcience of <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingent Events.</hi> About the year 400, when almoſt every body concerned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in condemning, and departing (as far as poſſible) from the opinions of <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen;</hi> the Anthropomorphite Doctrine, and its conſequences, were the <hi>Standard Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxy</hi> of many places, and were <hi>Hereſy</hi> no where. Even St. <hi>John Chryſoſtom</hi> at <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople</hi> hardly defended the <hi>Fratres Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi</hi> from the Proſecutions of <hi>Theophilus,</hi> Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop and Patriarch of <hi>Alexandria;</hi> who was a profeſt Anthropomorphite, and had expelled the <hi>Fratres Longi,</hi> for adhering to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97237:9"/>
                  <hi>Origen</hi>'s Doctrine of the Spirituality and Omnipreſence of God.</p>
               <p>But as I ſaid, we not only diſlike, but ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly reject the dangerous Doctrine, That God hath a Body, is like to Man; toge-with its conſequences, That he is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Omnipreſent, nor Omniſcient. It may as well be ſaid, he is not at all; nay this latter, tho the Anthropornorphites ſee it not, ſeems to be implied and included in the former. But we condemn not the <hi>Schechina</hi> or glorious Appearance of God in Heaven, which many Learned Men hold; nor the ſpiritual Body of Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="article">
               <p n="3">III. <hi>I believe farther concerning God, That there is no diſtinction of</hi> Perſons <hi>or</hi> Subſiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <hi>in God: And that the Son and Holy Ghoſt are not God: The former of them being only a Man; the latter no other than the</hi> Power <hi>or Operation of God. That there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of</hi> Merit <hi>in what Chriſt did or ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and that therefore he could not make</hi> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction <hi>for the Sins of the World.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> too much miſtakes. The queſtion is not at all concerning three <hi>Perſons,</hi> or three <hi>Subſiſtences</hi> in God: but whether there are three infinite <hi>Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtences;</hi> three eternal <hi>Minds</hi> and <hi>Spirits?</hi> We deny the latter with the whole Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97237:10"/>Church, againſt the Tritheiſts: We never queſtioned the former, <hi>Perſons</hi> or <hi>Subſiſtences;</hi> but only <hi>as Perſons are uſed or taken for Spirits, Minds and Beings.</hi> I ſhall explain this matter however more fully, in my Anſwer to the Biſhops of <hi>Worceſter, Sarum</hi> and <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> annexed to this <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement;</hi> or any one may ſee what is our ſenſe, <hi>in the Judgment of a diſintereſted Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, concerning the Controverſy between Dr.</hi> S—th, <hi>and Dr.</hi> Sherlock: <hi>By a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine of the Church of</hi> England. What that Author makes to be the Doctrine of <hi>the Nominals,</hi> and of <hi>the Church,</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Bleſſed Trinity, the Divinity of our Saviour, and the Satisfaction, is and ever was the belief of the Unitarians, as well as of the Catholick Church.</p>
               <p>But we ſay, the Lord Chriſt is only <hi>a Man,</hi> and the Holy Spirit only <hi>the Power</hi> of God. No, we ſay, our Lord Chriſt is <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man.</hi> He is <hi>Man,</hi> in reſpect of his reaſonable Soul, and human Body; <hi>God,</hi> in reſpect of <hi>God in him.</hi> Or more ſcholaſtically, in reſpect of the Hypoſtatical (or Perſonal) Union, of the Humanity of Chriſt with the Divinity. By which the Catholick Church means, and we mean, <hi>the Divinity was not only occaſionally aſſiſting to, but was</hi> (and <hi>is always</hi>) <hi>in Chriſt,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97237:10"/>illuminating, conducting and actuating him.</hi> More than this, is the Hereſy of <hi>Entyches,</hi> and leſs we never held: tho we confeſs that careleſs and leſs accurate Expreſſions, may have been uſed by both Parties; of which neither ought to take advantage againſt the other, when it appears there is no heterodox Intention.</p>
               <p>That by <hi>the Spirit</hi> of God is ſometimes meant (in Holy Scripture) <hi>the Power</hi> of God, cannot be denied: but concerning the Three Divine <hi>Perſons,</hi> we believe as the Catholick Church believes, That they are <hi>relative Subſiſtences,</hi> internal <hi>Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of the Deity to it ſelf. Or as the Schools, after St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> explain this; Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal <hi>unbegotten</hi> Wiſdom or Mind, reflex or <hi>begotten</hi> Wiſdom, called; in Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the <hi>Logos,</hi> and the eternal <hi>ſpiration</hi> of Divine Love.</p>
               <p>But do you not ſay, <q>There was <hi>no Merit</hi> in what Chriſt did or ſuffered: and that he could riot make <hi>ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> for our Sins?</q> He may for, our parts be <hi>Anathema,</hi> that teaches or believes that Doctrine. <hi>We</hi> believe that the Lord Chriſt by what he did and what he ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, was by the gracious acceptance of God, a true and <hi>perfect Propitiation</hi> for Sinners that repent, and turn to the good ways.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="article">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:97237:11"/>
               <p n="4">IV. In the next Article he makes us to believe a great many things; as <hi>that,</hi> 
                  <q>The firſt Man was not created in <hi>a ſtate of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>prightneſs.</hi>
                  </q> As if it were poſſible that men in their right ſenſes ſhould think the firſt Man was created <hi>a Sinner.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That</hi> 
                  <q>By his <hi>Fall Adam</hi> did not loſe <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> and Holineſs, which are part of <hi>the Image</hi> of God.</q> As who ſhould ſay, that by being a Sinner, he did <hi>not ſin,</hi> or become <hi>unlike</hi> to God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That</hi> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>Adam</hi>'s Poſterity have received <hi>no hurt</hi> nor <hi>ſtain</hi> by his Apoſtacy.</q> As if you ſhould ſay, that neither his <hi>bad Example,</hi> nor <hi>the Curſe</hi> that made the Earth ſo much leſs fruitful, was any <hi>hurt;</hi> and that the Rebellion of an Anceſtor, no not againſt God, is not <hi>any blot</hi> in his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily. I ſhall grow quite out of conceit with theſe Unitarians, if they ſay many more ſuch weak things. But in very deed I imagine Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> had a mind to have charged 'em more home; when he does, we ſhall conſider what to anſwer. I am of opinion that in this part of the Article he was ſomewhat aſhamed of his own Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; and that he feared to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and Party ridiculous, by a clear and diſtinct Repreſentation of their opinion.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:97237:11"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>That</hi> 
                  <q>Mankind, notwithſtanding <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi>'s <hi>fall,</hi> have by nature an ability to deſire and embrace all <hi>ſpiritual Good;</hi> and to avoid all that is ſinful or vitious.</q> They are <hi>bold Britains.</hi> What, embrace all the Goſpel-precepts by mere nature, when 'tis not poſſible ſo much as to know divers of them, but by <hi>Revelation Divine.</hi> And can they avoid too all that is vitious at all times, only by nature? In good truth, they are better and ſtronger by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, than I ever hope to be in this Life, by the (ſuperadded) Grace of God. But here again he did not ſtrike home; he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended more than he durſt ſay: and he durſt. not ſay it, leſt we ſhould ask him, whether he believes the juſt contrary?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That,</hi> 
                  <q>There is no need of the Spirit to repent, to believe, or to obey the Goſpel, and perform religious Acts.</q> 'Tis a ſerious point. We anſwer, with St. <hi>Paul, the Spirit HELPETH our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities,</hi> Rom. 8.26. But we judg for all that, the Holy Scripture gives no occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to any to turn Enthuſiaſts; and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve the whole duty we owe and muſt perform to God and to our Neighbor, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to preternatural Impulſes, as if we were Machines and not men; or Puppets, moved by inviſible Wires, not Men that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97237:12"/>act by their own <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Choice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That</hi> 
                  <q>Men are righteous before God, not by the merit of Chriſt, but by their own good works.</q> We anſwer, with all but Antinomians, and the more rigid Calviniſts: <hi>the Merit of Chriſt is not rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned to us, without Faith, and good Works of our own.</hi> But I am not certain, that the Calviniſts, or the Antinomiſts, would not aſſent to that Propoſition, or not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it to be orthodox: I incline to think thoſe People have no real difference with the Church, nor the Church with them; but that they miſtake one anothers meaning.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="article">
               <p n="5">V. Another branch of our Creed, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Mr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> runs thus: <hi>I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve concerning a future State,</hi> That <hi>the Souls of the Deceaſed have no knowledg or perception of any thing, they are not ſenſible of any Rewards or Pains: and that</hi> their very Nature is abſorpt.</p>
               <p>That at death, the Soul, as well as Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſleeps, was <hi>an error</hi> of ſome of the moſt ancient <hi>Fathers,</hi> as well as of <hi>ſome</hi> Unitarians. But neither of 'em ſaid, as Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> pretends, that in death the very Nature of the Soul is abſorpt, <hi>which is to ſay extinct:</hi> they both of them held, that there is a Reſurrection of the Soul,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97237:12"/>as well as Body. But why dos Mr. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> impute that opinion to us, when he has read, for he quotes the book, in the <hi>firſt Part</hi> of the <hi>Conſiderations on the Explications of the Trinity,</hi> what is our ſenſe of that matter? The words at <hi>p.</hi> 33. are theſe. <q>This <hi>Error</hi> was common to <hi>Socinus,</hi> and ſome of the Fathers. The Learned Mr. <hi>Du Pinn,</hi> in his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgment of the Fathers, has noted; that <hi>Juſtin Martyr, Irenaeus, Minutius Faelix,</hi> and <hi>Arnobius,</hi> were in this Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timent. There was no reaſon to object this to <hi>Socinus;</hi> as if it were a peculiar opinion of his: much leſs to the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Unitarians, who never defended it, nor (that I know of) do any of 'em hold it.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="article">
               <p n="6">VI. He ſays next; <hi>I believe we ſhall not riſe with the ſame Bodies, but that ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> Matter <hi>or</hi> Subſtance <hi>ſhall be ſubſtitut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in their place.</hi> I ſee moſt of our Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers have affected to miſtake our meaning concerning the reſurrection of the Body: We hold nothing that is ſingular in the caſe; we differ not from the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church about it. We ſay with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.35. <hi>How are the dead raiſed, and with what Bodies do they come?
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97237:13"/>—Thou ſoweſt not the body that ſhall be.</hi> The Body that is raiſed, is not in <hi>all</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects the <hi>ſame</hi> that was committed to the earth: in divers, perhaps in <hi>the moſt,</hi> it is. We riſe not <hi>Infants,</hi> or decrepit <hi>old Men,</hi> or <hi>lame,</hi> or <hi>deaf,</hi> or any way <hi>diſtort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;</hi> tho' many ſo lived, and ſo died. Nay, as to <hi>the Paſſions</hi> reſulting from the <hi>preſent</hi> complexion of the body, and therefore to be reckon'd the Modifications (and as it were parts) of the body; we riſe not with them; it is not the <hi>ſame</hi> Body, in reſpect of thoſe Paſſions that it here lived. For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, ſome are (by complexion) very cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardly, or penſive, or choleric, or jealous; <hi>the Body that ſhall be</hi> will not be ſuch: It will be conformed to the likeneſs of the glorious Body of our Lord Chriſt; that is, be freed from all (both external and internal) Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections. Farthermore, our preſent bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy (Phyſicians and Philoſophers ſay) is in a continual Flux; all the parts of it, internal as well as external, continually decay, and are continually alſo renewed. They decay by the Perſpiration, that is continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally cauſed by the internal heat; and are continually renewed by the Nouriſhment taken in, and converted into Blood, Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, Fleſh, and Bones. 'Tis ſaid, by the Learned in theſe matters, that no man's
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:97237:13"/>body is the very ſame, as to the matter and ſubſtance of it, this preſent year, that it was the laſt year, and will be the next year: 'Tis wholly new by the nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the preſent year. We ſay there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, there ſhall be a Reſurrection of the Body; and, as ſome of the Antient Creeds ſpoke, of the <hi>ſame</hi> Body; as truly and as properly as <hi>N.N.</hi> is the <hi>ſame Man</hi> this year that he was one, or ſeven, or twenty years ago. If Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> requires us to ſay more, he exacts more than the Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves: For by the Reſurrection of the <hi>ſame Body,</hi> the Church intends only, that 'tis as <hi>truly the ſame,</hi> as a Man (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Flux of his parts) is now the ſame <hi>N. N.</hi> or <hi>J. B.</hi> that he was ſeven or ten years paſt. Yet not <hi>altogether the ſame;</hi> becauſe inconceivably better: That is, without any external or internal Deformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties or Weakneſſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="article">
               <p n="7">VII. <hi>I believe that at the Day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Men ſhall not be required to give an account of their Actions; the moſt fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitious Sinners ſhall not</hi> be examined <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning any thing of their paſt Life: Only they ſhall be puniſhed; and their Puniſhment is this, to</hi> utterly <hi>ceaſe or periſh for ever. The unquenchable</hi> Fire <hi>is nothing but</hi> Anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilation.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:97237:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>I do not know that the Scriptures or the Catholic Church, do require any to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that Sinners ſhall <hi>be examined</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their paſt Life, at the day of the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Judgment. To what purpoſe, I pray, doth the All-knowing Judg need to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed concerning the particulars of their Gui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> If every perſon is to be ſeverally <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>ed,</hi> concerning the particulars of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>anſacted. Life; the Day of Judgment will extend it ſelf to many Millions of Ages more, and farther than the whole durati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the World, from its beginning to its conſummation. It ſhould ſeem Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> thinks, that becauſe the Scriptures ſpeak of the great Judgment by God, in the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of Men, and of Human Judicatures, ſuch as Trumpets, the Throne of the Judg, a formal Sentence, the Pleadings of the Guilty, the Anſwers of the Judg; that therefore in very deed, we are to expect ſuch a Scene at the Judgment by God, as at a common Aſſize. I conceive, on the contrary, that all ſuch expreſſions and words, wherever they are found in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, are not intended as real Deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; but as Compariſons, or Reſemblan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, by which the capacities of the Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar may he aſſiſted, and their affections wrought upon. All that is intended by
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:97237:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſuch expreſſions, is only this; that every one ſhall be ſo recompenſed at the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, as is worthy of the holy Judg and compaſſionate Father of the World.</p>
               <p>But we hold, he ſaith, that the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Wicked is only <hi>Extinction:</hi> Their life ſhall be deſtroyed for ever by the unquenchable Fire, into which they are caſt. Which opinion, that it may look ridiculous, he words for us thus; <hi>the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenchable</hi> Fire <hi>is nothing but</hi> Annihilation. What the Scriptures have ſaid concerning the Puniſhment of the Wicked, after the Reſurrection, is not ſo clear, but that the opinions of Learned Men, <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Moderns,</hi> have been very different about it. Some (of which number is <hi>Origen,</hi> the moſt conſiderable of the <hi>Ante-nicens</hi>) held, that not only wicked Men, but the very Devils, will repent, and reform under the Puniſhments they endure: that therefore, they will be pardoned, be admitted to a new trial of their Behaviour, and may attain to Bleſſedneſs. Theſe ſay, that <hi>Man</hi> being a reaſonable, is therefore a docile or teachable Creature: and it not looking probable, that the Wiſdom of God will loſe any part of his Creation, but will bring it to <hi>the Perfection,</hi> and upon that to <hi>the Bleſſedneſs,</hi> of which 'tis capable;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:97237:15"/>therefore, what by Inſtructions, what by Puniſhments, and Encouragements, God will reclame the Bad, will perfect and confirm the Good; and ſo in the long-run of things, be acclamed <hi>the Saviour of all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Others, among whom have been <hi>ſome</hi> (it may be <hi>the moſt</hi>) of the Forein <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> have thought, that the Righteous are rewarded with an everlaſting Life of Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs; and the <hi>impenitent Wicked</hi> puniſht by that unquenchable Fire, that will whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtroy their being. They believe this is the reaſon, why the Puniſhment by Hell-Fire is called Eternal <hi>Death</hi> in Holy Scripture. But the more current opinion among all denominations of Chriſtians is, that the Puniſhment of the Impenitent in Hell-fire, is called Death; not becauſe it utterly deſtroys the life of the Sufferer, but becauſe 'tis a continual and <hi>endleſs dying.</hi> The <hi>extreme pains</hi> of Hell may well be called <hi>an everlaſting dying,</hi> or an <hi>eternal Death;</hi> tho' the Sufferer is never extinct.</p>
               <p>I do not find any thing in the Books of the Engliſh <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians,</hi> concerning theſe opinions; they may hold as variouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them as the Chriſtians of other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominations. But if I may anſwer for them, by what I judg of them by conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation with them, I would ſay, we approve
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:97237:15"/>the doctrine delivered by Arch-biſhop <hi>J. Tillotſon,</hi> in a Sermon before her late Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of happy memory, <hi>March</hi> 7.1689. on <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.46. which Sermon was printed by their Majeſties ſpecial Command.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="article">
               <p n="8">VIII. <hi>I believe, as to Chriſtianity it ſelf, every thing in it is to be ſubmitted to the dictates of</hi> Human Reaſon: <hi>and that there are no Doctrines in it, that are myſterious.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neither of theſe was ever ſaid by any <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarian;</hi> and all our Prints, more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially thoſe in the Engliſh Tongue, are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, that there are many things, as well in Religion, as Nature, that are far above the capacity of human Reaſon, to declare or underſtand <hi>the manner of 'em;</hi> or how they ſhould be what we either ſee, or are <hi>infallibly</hi> taught they are. We never pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended that the <hi>Human Reaſon is the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Truth;</hi> as Mr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Norris</hi> charge us; ſo that what our reaſon does not comprehend, we will not believe on any other evidence whatſoever. We never ſaid it, or thought it; we reject no Doctrines but ſuch as are <hi>contrary to Reaſon,</hi> and of that I ſpeak fully in the anſwer to Mr. <hi>De Luzancy,</hi> hereto annexed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="article">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:97237:16"/>
               <p n="9">IX. <hi>As to Divine Worſhip, I believe it may be given to another beſides God; to Chriſt, who is</hi> but a Creature.</p>
               <p>But we have diſavowed nothing more, in all our Prints, than giving Divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to any, but only God: that 'tis a marvel to me, that Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> ſhould im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute to us ſuch a doctrine; we have ſcarce any Engliſh Print where we do not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly oppoſe it. Nor do we reckon of the Lord Chriſt as <hi>but a Creature;</hi> I have ſaid before, he is <hi>God and Man.</hi> The Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity did ſo inhabit in the Humanity of Chriſt; doth ſo exert in it the moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious effects of Omnipotence and Omniſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; that if others have been called God, becauſe <hi>they repreſented God,</hi> Chriſt is to be ſo called, becauſe <hi>he exhibits God.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="article">
               <p n="10">X. <hi>I believe, Prayer was not required un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Old Teſtament. The</hi> Lords-day <hi>is a ceremonious Obſervance, aboliſhed by the Goſpel. There is no ſpiritual Bleſſing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred in the uſe of the Sacraments. Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm is an uſeleſs Rite; and the Baptiſm of Children altogether vain. There is no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct function, or office of Miniſters, in the Chriſtian Church; the very Lord's Supper it ſelf may be adminiſtred by a private perſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:97237:16"/>
               <p>I think Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> is in the right a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe (if any ſuch there were) who deny'd that Prayer was a duty or precept of the Old Teſtament and the Law; when he ſays, <q>It is included in the general pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of fearing, ſerving, worſhipping God.</q> But he is as much out in the next Article, that ſome have ſaid, the <hi>Lords<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> is aboliſhed by the Goſpel: for it was never ſaid by any. He meant, I ſuppoſe, that the Seventh-day, or <hi>Sabbath,</hi> is abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſht: and I take it to be the doctrine of the Catholic Church, that the <hi>Seventh-day-Sabbath</hi> was ceremonial, and is abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſht. It may better, however, be ſaid, that the Sabbath <hi>is transferred</hi> from the ſeventh to the firſt day; than that 'tis <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely aboliſht,</hi> or taken away. In ſhort, the Engliſh <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> hold no private o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion about either the Sabbath, or Lord's day; but, as well in principle as pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, concur with the Catholic Church.</p>
               <p>It is too looſly ſaid, <q>That there is no ſpiritual Bleſſing conferr'd in the uſe of the Sacraments.</q> For there is no ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God, but the ſerious and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout performance of it draws a bleſſing on the doer. For all that, many exceed in aſcribing to the Sacraments certain Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Energies, without competent
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:97237:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>warrant from the Word of God. I do not know that Baptiſm is any thing more than <hi>a federal Rite,</hi> by which we are initiated into the Chriſtian Religion: or the <hi>Holy Supper</hi> any thing more than <hi>a commemorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Sacrifice of Chriſt,</hi> offering him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to God as an atonement for repenting ſinners. I know not to what purpoſe ſo many ſuperſtitious Books are written, to teach people how to prepare themſelves for the <hi>Memorial Supper;</hi> when an <hi>honeſt</hi> Intention, and a <hi>reverent</hi> Performance, are ſufficient, both <hi>preparations</hi> and <hi>qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, for</hi> and <hi>in</hi> all Goſpel-Ordinances. The Apoſtle ſays, <hi>He that eateth that</hi> Bread <hi>unworthily, or unworthily drinketh of that</hi> Cup, <hi>is guilty of the blood of Chriſt;</hi> nay, <hi>eateth and drinketh</hi> Judgment <hi>to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</hi> But he alſo warns them, what he means by <hi>unworthy partaking,</hi> namely, their not tarrying for one another; and withal, eating and drinking with ſo little regard to God or Men, that <hi>ſome of them made themſelves drunk with the Sacramental Wine,</hi> while others could not ſo much as taſt of it. Briefly, their aſſembling to this ſolemn <hi>commemorative Sacrifice,</hi> was more like to <hi>a Carouſal,</hi> than to a celebration of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Bleſſed memory of a dying Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. Theſe were the Diſorders and Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularities
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:97237:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>concerning which they were <hi>to examin themſelves;</hi> and thereby avoid an unworthy Communicating, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences thereof.</p>
               <p>We do not ſay, <q>Baptiſm is an <hi>uſeleſs Rite;</hi> or that the Baptiſm of Children is <hi>altogether vain.</hi>
                  </q> What the Wiſdom of God has appointed to <hi>all Nations,</hi> is not to be eſteemed <hi>uſeleſs;</hi> tho' we our ſelves knew not the uſes of it: and it is uſe enough that this Sacrament is <hi>an initiating Rite.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor is it a good Exception againſt this Sacrament's being continued ſtill; that <hi>now</hi> people are Chriſtians <hi>by Education:</hi> Seeing there is the <hi>ſame</hi> reaſon for <hi>its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance</hi> as for <hi>its inſtitution,</hi> namely, a ſolemn, public, and formal <hi>Initiation into the Religion of Jeſus.</hi> And this may, in ſome ſenſe, be done <hi>in Infancy,</hi> by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervention of Undertakers, commonly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led God-fathers; and how it can be done without 'em I ſee not. But it is without all reaſon, that Parents ſhould not be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be Undertakers, when others <hi>cannot,</hi> or cannot <hi>eaſily</hi> be had. It were well, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks, if the Miniſter and Church-War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens (together with the Parents) were obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to be Undertakers <hi>ex Officio,</hi> or <hi>ratione
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:97237:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>Officii,</hi> by their Place and Office; and it were yet better, if the whole Church un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook for the Infants. Moreover, where <hi>Infant-Baptiſm</hi> is the cuſtom of the Church, <hi>Confirmation</hi> (or the perſon's taking upon himſelf the Covenant and Promiſes that were made in his name by his Undertakers) ought to be as little neglected as <hi>Baptiſm:</hi> nay, the perſon cannot be ſaid to be a <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Chriſtian,</hi> or to be Chriſtianly bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, till he is conſumed; that is, has publickly taken upon himſelf his Baptiſmal Engagements.</p>
               <p>Paedo-baptiſm, or <hi>Infant-Baptiſm,</hi> and <hi>ſprinkling</hi> inſtead of <hi>dipping,</hi> have occaſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an unneceſſary Seiſm from the Church; for neither of theſe are Doctrines of the Church, or impoſed on any. The Church requires <hi>dipping,</hi> except in caſe of Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity or Danger. The words of the <hi>Rubric,</hi> in the Office of Baptiſm, are theſe. <q>If they (the Godfathers) certify, that the Child may well endure it: He (the Miniſter) ſhall <hi>dip</hi> it, dip <hi>the Child,</hi> in the Water; ſaying, I baptize thee, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> —But if they certify that the Child is weak; it ſhall ſuffice to <hi>pour Water upon it.</hi>
                  </q> Neither of theſe is ſprinkling, they are both of them Baptiſm
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:97237:18"/>(or <hi>Waſhing</hi>) in the ſtricteſt ſenſe of the word. As to Infant-Baptiſm, it doth not certainly appear, that it was not practiſed by the Apoſtles; rather it ſeemeth, that when the Parents were baptized, so also were the Children: for ſuch was the cuſtom of the <hi>Jews</hi> toward their Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites, from whom Baptiſm, the Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Supper, and in a word, all the anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Eccleſiaſtical Rites, and Church-Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline (Hierarchy or Church-Government) was taken by our Saviour and the Apoſtles. Notwithſtanding, for ſatisfaction of ſuch as do not approve Infant-Baptiſm; the Church has an Office, called in the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, <hi>the Baptiſm of ſuch as are of riper years.</hi> That as I ſaid, the ſeiſm of the People and Churches, that are vulgarly called Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, or Anabaptiſts, ſeems not well grounded.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, as to that, <q>I believe there is no diſtinct Function or Office of <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters:</hi> and that the very Lord's Supper may be adminiſtred by a private Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</q>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer for my ſelf, and moſt other (if not <hi>all</hi>) Unitarians. There is <hi>a</hi> three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold diſtinction of Church-Officers, by themſelves modeſtly called Miniſters:
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:97237:19"/>namely, Biſhops, Presbyters, or Prieſts and Deacons. The two former ſeem to be of Divine Right: the other of Apoſtolical Inſtitution only; and that too (as appears from <hi>Acts</hi> 6.3, 4.) not by any particular Inſpiration, but meerly on Motives of Prudence and Charity. Theſe three Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Biſhop, Prieſt and Deacon, are of that Antiquity, and Univerſality, that <hi>as ſoon as,</hi> and <hi>whereſoever</hi> Chriſtianity was profeſſed, the Churches were go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd after this form. A form received among all <hi>the Sects</hi> of Chriſtians, as well as by the ſounder part of 'em, called com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly the Church: till Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> in <hi>a caſe of Neceſſity,</hi> introduced a new ſort of Church-Adminiſtration. Theſe are they to whom only (except in <hi>caſe of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity,</hi> ſuch as <hi>the Reformation</hi> was) it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to adminiſter the Sacraments; and to inſtruct and exhort publickly. But what makes <hi>a caſe of neceſſity,</hi> is a queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by it ſelf, on which I do not here en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: I wiſh the Church had not given, or may never give cauſe to the Unitarians, either by Excluſion or Perſecution, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful or over-harſh Terms of' Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, to have recourſe to Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi>'s Expedient.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="article">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:97237:19"/>
               <p n="11">XI. <hi>As to moral Points, I believe that</hi> officious Lies <hi>are lawful; the motions of</hi> Concupiſcence <hi>not vitious; idle or obſcene words, Gluttony, Drunkenneſs, Riot, Lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ury, and impure Deſires and Luſts, were not forbidden till Chriſt's time.</hi> By <hi>officious Lies</hi> are meant thoſe <hi>Falſities</hi> that do good to ſome, without doing hurt to others; as the Lie of the Hebrew Midwives to <hi>Pharaoh;</hi> the Tale of <hi>Michal</hi> to her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Saul,</hi> when ſhe ſuffer'd <hi>David</hi> to eſcape; and <hi>Jonathan</hi>'s feigned excuſe for <hi>David,</hi> when he hid <hi>David</hi> from his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Anger, <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.19. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.17. and 20.6. To officious Lies belong alſo Compliments, very low Bowings, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectful Carriage towards Perſons for whom we have not the kindneſs or regard of which we make flow, by thoſe exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and <hi>falſe</hi> Significations. I think it may excuſe <hi>Volkelius,</hi> whom Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> cites for this part of his Charge; that the officious Lies of the Midwives, of <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal,</hi> and of <hi>Jonathan,</hi> are related in Scripture without blaming them: they are not cenſured by the Inſpired Writers; they are told by the Prophets <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Samuel,</hi> without the leaſt ſignification that they were Sins. <hi>Volkelius</hi> might infer
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:97237:20"/>from hence that the Texts which forbid lying and falſeneſs, are intended of ſuch lying as is <hi>hurtful</hi> or <hi>prejudicial</hi> to others; and that what dos no hurt, can be the Subject of no forbidding Law. To for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid what helps ſome, even to the ſaving of Life or Goods, without any hurt or wrong to another: why ſhould any Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver, who reſpects at all the good of his People, ſo enact?</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding, I think Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> ſays well. <q>If once ſuch Doctrine is commonly taught, all Lies will be reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſome way or other <hi>officious;</hi> and Truth and Sincerity will be baniſht from the Earth.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>The motions of <hi>Concupiſcence</hi> are not vitious or ſinful.</q> By <hi>Concupiſcence</hi> is meant ſome unlawful Deſire or Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ariſing in the mind; but not conſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to, or put into practice. Methinks, ſo far forth as ſuch Motions in the mind are <hi>involuntary,</hi> they ſhould rather be called Frailties than Sins; and the diſapproving and reſiſting them ſhall be rewarded by God. Concerning <q>obſcene Words, Riot, Gluttony, Drunkenneſs, impure Deſires, not forbidden by <hi>the Law;</hi> and not ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unlawful, till prohibited by the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel:</q>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:97237:20"/>We are not much concerned in ſuch a Diſpute; it being granted on all hands, that they are forbid in the Writings of the New Teſtament. Notwithſtanding, I wonder that any ſhould ſay, they are not prohibited in the Moſaick Law. Some of them were puniſhable with death by that Law: as Gluttony and Drunkenneſs, by the Law at <hi>Deut.</hi> 21.20. Luxury, Riot, Luſt, and ſuch like, are contrary to the good of a Man's Children, and of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; or of his Neighbor and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth; and therefore are implicitly forbid by that Commandment, at <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.18. which requires that a man ſhould love his Neighbor as himſelf. I do not love my Neighbor as my ſelf, if I am guilty of <hi>Luxury</hi> or <hi>Riot,</hi> by which my <hi>Heir,</hi> and the Poor are defrauded; or if I am guilty of Ambition, Covetouſneſs, or Luſt, by which I ſpoil, or grind, or wrong my Neighbor. Nay, Luſt, Riot, Exceſs, Covetouſneſs, do unfit us, and that very much for the ſervice of God, and for the honeſt and honorable diſcharge of our ſtation, whatſoever that be in the Commonwealth: therefore we may ſay, they are <hi>implicitely</hi> forbidden, by all thoſe Commandments of the Law, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire either the Fear, Regard, and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:97237:21"/>of God; or the welfare and eſteem of our Neighbor or Selves.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="article">
               <p n="12">XII. <hi>Concerning Magiſtrates, I believe 'tis not lawful for them, under the Goſpel, to inflict Capital Puniſhment</hi> (Death) <hi>on any Offenders; no not on Murderers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This was the Doctrine of divers of the Fathers of the three firſt Ages; ſcarce any of 'em believ'd otherwise. Nay they added, 'tis not lawful to go to the Wars, as a Souldier or Officer; or to aſſiſt at Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions; or even to defend a Mans own Life, by any ſuch reſiſtance as will take away the Life of the injurious Aggreſſor. The reaſon they gave for this <hi>laſt</hi> was, that by killing a Perſon who attempts to murder me, he is diſpatched out of the world <hi>without Repentance,</hi> and therefore is certainly damn'd: but the Chriſtian, by being killed, loſes only his Life, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters upon a bleſſed Immortality. Some Unitarians have been of this mind, while others have written againſt the whole Doctrine. In ſhort, it is not their Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, as Unitarians; for ſome of them have held it, while others (I believe, the moſt) diſallow it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="article">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:97237:21"/>
               <p n="13">XIII. <hi>Concerning ſome other points, I believe as the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>believes; for we agree with them in ſeveral points of Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trin.</hi> What theſe points are, he tells us at <hi>Chap.</hi> 9. from <hi>p.</hi> 201. Namely, <hi>that</hi> ſomethings were ſaid by our Saviour, by way only of monition or counſel, not of command. <hi>That</hi> we merit by a good Life, and may be perfect. <hi>That</hi> all Sins are not damnable. <hi>That</hi> the prayers of the living may help the dead. Nay the Author of <hi>the Conſiderations on the Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Trinity,</hi> ſpeaks favourably of the Tranſubſtantiation.</p>
               <p>Let us begin at the foot of this account. The Author of <hi>the Conſiderations,</hi> is no otherwiſe favourable to the Doctrine of the Tranſubſtantiation, than by ſaying of it, <q>'Tis only a Philoſophical <hi>Error</hi> or <hi>Folly;</hi> not an Impiety, <bibl>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 21.</bibl>
                  </q> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, <hi>p.</hi> 22. <q>'Tis <hi>a Miſtake</hi> into which the Papiſts have been cozened by the Philoſophy of <hi>Ariſtotle.</hi>
                  </q> Would Mr. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> think a man favoured the Doctrines in his Books, if he gave them no better Names than <hi>Miſtakes, Errors</hi> and <hi>Follies?</hi> Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> finds <hi>Impiety, Irreligion, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſm,</hi> and what not, in all Doctrines, and all Authors he diſlikes: We are no ſo dextrous. We ſometimes think
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:97237:22"/>that we ſpy <hi>an Error</hi> or <hi>Miſtake;</hi> and ſometimes it ſeems ſo groſs as to deſerve the name of <hi>a Folly:</hi> but to call it Impiety, Irreligion, Abnegation of Chriſtianity; how much ſoever Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> delights in it, and makes it his conſtant Practice as well in preaching as writing; we cannot approve the Example, it being always contrary to Charity, good Manners, and Truth.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>The Prayers of this Living may help the Dead.</q> Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> quotes for this but one Socinian Writer; nor is that Author poſitive in the caſe. He only ſays; <q>Thoſe who believe <hi>a middle ſtate</hi> or place for the Dead, do well to pray for them: That is, in caſe you ſuppoſe, beſide Heaven and Hell, ſome <hi>middle place</hi> where Souls may repent and reform, or are any otherwiſe capable of mercy, or where they have not yet received their laſt Doom: It is Charity to interceed by our Prayers for them, as much as we would for the Living.</q> I believe he is the only Writer of his Sect, that can be charged with any ſuch thing: but we have it in print, concerning a late Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> Dr.<hi>Sheldon;</hi> that he prayed for the Dead in his <hi>daily Prayers.</hi> But what one particular Man dos or ſays, is
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:97237:22"/>not to be imputed to his whole Party, and reported to the whole world <hi>as an Article of their Creed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>All Sins are <hi>not damnable.</hi> A Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian <hi>may merit</hi> by his good works, and may <hi>be perfect.</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <hi>Merit</hi> and <hi>Perfection</hi> may be <hi>truly</hi> or <hi>falſly</hi> ſaid of the works and life of a Chriſtian man; according as you interpret the terms Merit and Perfection. Taking 'em in the ſenſe that Proteſtants uſe them; no Man can merit of God, the infinite Recompences of Heaven, and of Bleſſedneſs everlaſting: nor was any Man perfect, or without Sin; but only <hi>that Lamb of God that taketh away the Sins of the world.</hi> But Merit and Perfection are ſometimes uſed in a popular ſenſe; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for that, tho imperfect, yet <hi>ſincere Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> to God's Commandments, to which God has graciouſly appointed <hi>the recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence</hi> of everlaſting Bleſſedneſs in Heaven: and for <hi>univerſal Obedience,</hi> as it is oppoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (not to Overſights and Frailties, but) a <hi>wilful indulging</hi> our ſelves in particular Sins. In this ſenſe every ſincere Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an both <hi>merits</hi> and <hi>is perfect.</hi> Yet, I own that divers Unitarian Writers have ſpoke either too looſly, or too incorrectly on the point of Perfection; but they have been as much oppoſed, by ſome of their own
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:97237:23"/>number. The ſame cannot be ſaid, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the diſtinction of Sin into mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal and venial; for our People are poſitive and unanimous, that as St. <hi>John</hi> words this matter, <hi>there is a Sin which is not unto death,</hi> 1 John 5.16. God Almighty, they ſay, has not appointed Hell-fire to our Frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Inadvertences; but to our <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts</hi> and <hi>adviſed Breach</hi> of his Laws.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Some things ſaid by our Saviour, are Counſels to ſuch as would be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect; not abſolute indiſpenſible Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands to all the Faithful without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception.</q> He quotes for this, an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure paſſage of one ſingle Socinian Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, who never was eſpouſed in that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by any of his Party. We judg that the diſtinction of Counſels and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, is a great and very dangerous Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption; a back-door by which to eſcape from almoſt a mans whole Duty. The two Doctrines of <hi>Counſels for the perfect</hi> and <hi>probable Opinions,</hi> will furniſh the moſt profligate Wretch in the world, with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences and excuſes for his very greateſt Enormities.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, after all, I believe, <hi>Tho the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Articles are all of 'em neceſſary to make a Man</hi> a Socinian: <hi>yet the belief of only one
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:97237:23"/>of them, is enough to make a Man</hi> a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian; <hi>and that one Article is,</hi> that Jeſus is the Meſſias: <hi>In which it is not included, whether he be</hi> God <hi>or</hi> Man, <hi>or whether he ſatisfied Divine</hi> Juſtice <hi>for our Sins by</hi> his Death; <hi>but only that a Man of</hi> Nazareth <hi>was ordained, and ſent by God to be a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſee all Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> his Colts-teeth are not yet out of his head; he cannot forbear dealing ſometimes in Railery and Wit: but I muſt ſeriouſly deſire him to name me any Socinian or Unitarian Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that ever ſaid, no more is required to make <hi>a Chriſtian,</hi> but only that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve <hi>Jeſus is the Meſſias.</hi> The truth of the matter is this; Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> has been lately very much foiled, firſt by a Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Gentleman, then by a Divine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> upon this Queſtion; <q>Whether it be of the eſſence of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian <hi>as a Chriſtian,</hi> to aſſent to more than this one Article, that <hi>Jeſus is the Meſſias, ſent by God to inſtruct and ſave the World?</hi>
                  </q> They do not doubt that 'tis a Chriſtians duty to learn (by degrees) all the other Articles of the Chriſtian Creed, and to believe them; but if he hath attained, or (by occaſion of <hi>what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever Impediments,</hi> that were not cauſed
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:97237:24"/>by his own <hi>Negligence</hi> or <hi>Perverſneſs</hi>) he can attain to more either Knowledg or Faith; yet this one Article doth make him a Chriſtian. It doth not ſatisfy Mr. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards,</hi> that upon all the points in queſtion, they have declared themſelves to be Anti-Socinians: he reſolves for all that they ſhall be <hi>Socinians;</hi> and this opinion which they maintain againſt him, <hi>a new Article</hi> of the Socinian Creed. It may be one way he thinks to reduce 'em to ſilence, if he calls their opinion Socinianiſm: and if after that they will not pull in their Horns, it ſhall be Irreligion or downright Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſm, or at leaſt abnegation of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or Popery; his other Compliments to thoſe whom he is pleaſed to attack.</p>
               <p>I have now anſwered concerning all the Articles of our Religion with ſincerity, without any the leaſt diſguiſe; or reſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or unuſual meaning or meanings. And I am not ſorry that Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> almoſt conſtrained us to explain our ſelves con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning theſe points. For as unſincere and untrue as his Imputations are, and as ſcurrilous as his manner of repreſenting them and diſcourſing upon them ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times is: the Retortion or Anſwer here made, will be judged by indifferent and diſcerning Perſons, to be home and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory.</p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:97237:24"/>
               <p>As to the man himſelf, Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> has been ſerviceable to the common Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, by divers learned Books: therefore I wiſh to him whatſoever good, himſelf deſires to himſelf, theſe Concertations between us notwithſtanding.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>THIS <hi>Scheme</hi> as it expreſſes the real Sentiments of the <hi>Socinians;</hi> ſo it perfectly agrees with the Doctrine of the Catholick Church, and of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> ſaving that in the fourth Article, concerning <hi>Original Sin, Freewill</hi> and <hi>Grace,</hi> the Anſwer is not ſo explicit and direct as it would have been if Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> had not affectedly declined to declare and expreſs the Doctrine of the Church concerning thoſe matters. In their firſt Riſe, the Unitarians followed the Doctrine of St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Calvin,</hi> in the Article of <hi>Original Sin;</hi> and the depending Articles, <hi>Free-will</hi> and the <hi>Grace</hi> of God: but <hi>F. Socinus</hi> coming into <hi>Tranſilvania,</hi> and then into <hi>Poland,</hi> reviv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed among 'em <hi>the Pelagian Doctrine;</hi> ſo that for about an Age they were <hi>Pelagians,</hi> in the queſtion of <hi>Original Sin,</hi> and its <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents.</hi> In this laſt Century, as they ſpeak, or Age, being the ſeventeenth from the birth of our Saviour, thoſe Queſtions
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:97237:25"/>have received a new turn in all the We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern Churches: that is to ſay, among the Roman Catholicks; and the Proteſtants of all denominations. A kind of <hi>Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelagianiſm</hi> is grown into repute in moſt places, being a temper or expedient of Peace, both Parties yielding ſomewhat; and yet both retaining enough to make their Doctrine conſiſtent with our natural No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Mercy</hi> of God. And to this I think the Unitarians now rather encline; but not generally, that is, not univerſally, or not <hi>all of them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In ſhort, the above-recited Scheme is <hi>direct</hi> and clear: except only in the fourth Article concerning Original Sin; and the Points thereon depending. But thoſe Queſtions being now <hi>variouſly</hi> held in all Churches, and among all Parties: the <hi>Socinians</hi> are no more Diſſenters on the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of what ſome, or moſt of them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve concerning that Article; than Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Jer. Taylor</hi> (for inſtance) and Dr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> and the <hi>Remonſtrant Party,</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be the greater part of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> are. So that upon the whole we may ſay, <hi>There is now no Sociniun Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy.</hi> The miſunderſtanding that was common to both Parties, the Church and the Unitarians, is annihilated: and Mr.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:97237:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Firmin,</hi> by approving and publiſhing the Scheme of Agreement, <hi>profeſſed</hi> himſelf of the ſame mind with the Catholick Church, and the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> was ſenſible of this; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding as Curator of the Unitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an an Religion, he reſolved to have continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his endeavours, that no <hi>falſe</hi> Notion o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>the Trinity</hi> ſhould corrupt the ſincere Faith of <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</hi> He was perſwaded that the Faith of the Unity is the firſt Article of Chriſtianity; the Article that diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhes Chriſtians from Pagans: as the belief of <hi>the Meſſiah already come,</hi> diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhes us from <hi>Jews.</hi> He judged that tho the unſcriptural terms <hi>Trinity, three Divine Perſons,</hi> and ſuch like, <hi>in the ſenſe they are intended by the Church,</hi> contain a Doctrine which is true; yet taken <hi>in the ſenſe they bear in common familiar Speech,</hi> in which ſenſe the greater number of men (almoſt all the unlearned) muſt needs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand them; they imply a more groſs and abſurd Polytheiſm, than any of the old Heathens were guilty of. He that underſtands three Divine <hi>Perſons</hi> to be three (diſtinct, infinite, all-perfect) <hi>Spirits</hi> or <hi>Beings</hi> or <hi>Minds,</hi> three <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,</hi> three ſeveral Objects of Worſhip, is more guilty of Polytheiſm, than the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:97237:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Greeks</hi> or <hi>Romans</hi> ever were before their converſion to Chriſtianity: for tho they and other Nations were Heathens, that is, Polytheiſts, Aſſerters of more Gods; yet they never believed more than <hi>one Infinite All-perfect Spirit,</hi> the Father and King of the <hi>leſſer Deities.</hi> Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> knew well that the Majority of vulgar Chriſtians, and not a few Learned Men, have a Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſtick Notion or Conception of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> or three Divine Perſons, each of which is God: namely, that they are three diſtinct Infinite All-perfect <hi>Minds</hi> or <hi>Spirits.</hi> Meeting this every day in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation as well as in Books; he was not leſs zealous for the Doctrine of the Unity, after the Publication of the Scheme of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement, than before. And therefore he purpoſed, beſides the continuation of all his former Efforts, to hold Aſſemblies for Divine Worſhip, diſtinct from the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of any other denomination of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. But he did not intend theſe Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies or Congregations by way of ſciſm or ſeparation from the Church; but only <hi>as Fraternities in the Church,</hi> who would undertake a more eſpecial care of that Article, for the ſake of which 'tis cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain both the <hi>Teſtaments</hi> were written. The great deſign and ſcope of both Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:97237:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>and the reaſon that they were gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by God, was to regain Mankind to the belief and acknowledgment of <hi>but one God:</hi> to deſtroy Polytheiſm of all ſorts. Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> intended to recommend it to the Unitarian Congregations, as the very reaſon of their diſtinct aſſembling; to be particularly mindful of, and zealous for, the Article of the Unity; to cauſe it to be ſo explained in their Aſſemblies, Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſms and Books (without denying, or ſo much as ſuppreſſing the Catholick Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the Trinity) that all men might eaſily and readily know in what ſenſe <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of God</hi> is to be believed, and the Myſtery of <hi>a Trinity of Divine Perſons (each of them God)</hi> is to be interpreted. Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> feared, that without ſuch Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, the continual uſe of terms, which <hi>in their ordinary ſignification</hi> are confeſſed by all to imply three Gods, would paganize in ſome time the whole Chriſtian Church; which is Heathen already in the majori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of its Members, by occaſion of thoſe terms: and that no ſufficient care is taken to interpret them to the people.</p>
               <p>I though to have ended here: but the Dean of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> having publiſhed a large Book in Quarto, to which he gives the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of <hi>the preſent ſtate of the</hi> Socinian <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy:</hi>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:97237:27"/>I think my ſelf obliged to take notice of it, and make a fit Anſwer to it. In order whereunto, it will be even neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to conſider alſo, briefly, his former Books: indeed my Anſwer will be little more than a comparing the Doctrine of theſe Books with this laſt; in which, as to his Notions, (tho propos'd commonly in ſomewhat improper, unconvenient, and dangerous expreſſions) he has given ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to Dr. <hi>S—th,</hi> and the <hi>Oxford</hi> Heads; in other words, he is become tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Catholic, and perfectly Unitarian.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> had cauſed to be written <hi>a brief Hiſtory of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians,</hi> and <hi>brief Notes on the Creed of</hi> Athanaſius, in the years 1689 and 1690. Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> was then more at leiſure than he deſired; ſo he anſwered in a wrathful Book, entituled, <hi>A Vindication of the Doctrine of the H. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</hi> In this Vindication he lays about him for that ſort of Trinity, that had been oppos'd in the aforeſaid Hiſtory and Notes: a Trinity of (Infinite, Eternal, All-per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect) <hi>Minds, Beings,</hi> and <hi>Spirits.</hi> The Doctrine of his Book, may be ſumm'd into this following ſhort Abſtract.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>The H. Trinity is three <hi>ſuch</hi> Perſons as are <hi>ſubſtantially diſtinct;</hi> or are <hi>three diſtinct Spiritual Subſtances.</hi> Being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:97237:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <hi>Perſons,</hi> they muſt needs be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct <hi>Subſtances; Perſons</hi> and <hi>intelligent Subſtances,</hi> being reciprocal terms, or ſignifying the ſame thing. The Divine Perſons are three <hi>Beings,</hi> three <hi>Spirits,</hi> three <hi>Minds,</hi> as diſtinct as three human Perſons, as diſtinct as <hi>Peter, James,</hi> and <hi>John.</hi> Each of theſe Minds or Spirits has a diſtinct <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, Wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>Will,</hi> of his own; a diſtinct abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely-perfect <hi>Wiſdom, Goodneſs,</hi> and <hi>Power; for theſe perfections may be, and are, in more than one.</hi> And as each of them is an all-perfect Spirit; each of them alſo is <hi>a God.</hi> Yet are they not three Gods; becauſe being internally conſcious to each others thoughts and actions: by means of this <hi>mutual conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,</hi> tho they are three all-perfect Spirits, and each of them <hi>a God,</hi> they are but one God.</q>
               </p>
               <p>If we will ſay truth, Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> was no more overſeen in this explication of the Trinity, than the principal Divines and Preachers at <hi>London,</hi> and both Univerſities. To my knowledg, they upbraided Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> with this Book of Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s: and ſome of them told him; If Dr. <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock</hi>'s Book did not reclame him from his Hereſy, it would riſe up in Judgment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:97237:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>him. It came forth <hi>cum licentiâ ſuperiorum:</hi> and ſhortly after, the Doctor was reſtored to all his Preferments, which he had forfeited by refuſing the Oaths to the Government; with the addition of the Deanary of St. <hi>Pauls.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But neither the Canonical Licenſe, nor the new and great Preferment, nor the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probations and applauſes from ſo many (and ſo conſiderable) Fautors, could pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent a moſt terrible after-clap. For to ſay nothing of the Anſwer, firſt by the Socini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and then by Dr. <hi>S—th;</hi> the Heads of Colleges at <hi>Oxford, Nov.</hi> 25. 1695, made and ordered the publication of this Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and Decree. <q>Theſe words, <hi>there are three diſtinct</hi> Minds <hi>and</hi> Subſtances <hi>in the Trinity;</hi> and theſe words, <hi>the three Perſons in the Trinity, are three di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct infinite</hi> Minds <hi>or</hi> Spirits, <hi>and three individual Subſtances;</hi> are Erroneous, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical, and Impious. And we require all perſons, who are committed to our inſtitution or care, that they affirm no ſuch Doctrine, either by preaching or otherwiſe.</q>
               </p>
               <p>When this Decree came abroad, Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s former Abettors deſerted him in whole troops: and now they ſaid, Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities ſpeak but ſeldom, and by way of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:97237:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>Authority, without giving the reaſons of their Decrees; but as they interpoſe but rarely, and in important Caſes, 'tis always with certainty. In ſhort, from this time, Doctor <hi>Sherlock</hi> was left almoſt alone. That I know of, the ſame Doctors, Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries, Deans, Biſhops, who had boaſted of his Book (not only as orthodox, but) as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſwerable; now tackt about, and as much approved the <hi>Oxford</hi>-Decree. The moſt now ſaid, it was even neceſſary to make and publiſh the Decree: <hi>Tritheiſm</hi> being ſo much worſe than <hi>Sabellianiſm</hi> or <hi>Socini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aniſm,</hi> as Paganiſm or <hi>Heatheniſm</hi> is worſe than mere <hi>Judaiſm;</hi> there is no body but will prefer the faith of the Jews, tho' ſo unperfect, before the many Gods of the Heathens. Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> was often told of theſe murmurs, and that they were grown general: his anſwer was, that <hi>he was ſure that he was in the right.</hi> And accordingly he ſhortly publiſhed his <hi>Examination of the</hi> Oxford-<hi>Decree.</hi> In this <hi>Examination</hi> he often repeats his former doctrine. He ſays, for inſtance, P. 46. <q>Theſe <hi>Decreeing</hi> and <hi>Hereſy-making</hi> Heads of Colleges, have condemned the <hi>true</hi> Catholic Faith, the <hi>Nicene</hi> Faith, and the Faith of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </q> He adds in the ſame page, <q>Three <hi>Divine</hi> Perſons, who
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:97237:29"/>are not three diſtinct Minds and Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, is not greater <hi>Hereſy,</hi> than 'tis <hi>Nonſenſe.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>P. 31. <q>The preſent diſpute is about <hi>three diſtinct infinite</hi> Minds <hi>and</hi> Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <hi>in the Trinity;</hi> whether this be Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholic doctrine, and Catholic language? If it appears that they <hi>(the Fathers)</hi> owned three diſtinct <hi>Subſtances,</hi> both name and thing; there can be no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute about three <hi>Minds.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>P. 23. <q>If God begets no <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> he begets nothing that is <hi>real;</hi> —And then, neither is God a <hi>real</hi> Father, nor the Son a <hi>real</hi> Son.</q>
               </p>
               <p>P. 22. <q>If a Divine Perſon, <hi>as a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> and <hi>as a diſtinct Perſon</hi> from the other two Perſons, be not <hi>an infinite Mind;</hi> there is an end of the Chriſtian Trinity.</q>
               </p>
               <p>P. 18. <q>The three Perſons muſt be as diſtinct Minds, Spirits, and Subſtances, as they are diſtinct Perſons.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Every body diſliked this Anſwer to the <hi>Oxford</hi> Heads; it was owned to be Hereſy, <hi>in excelſis:</hi> Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s more warm Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers call'd out for the ſitting of <hi>a Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> to cenſure ſuch a manifeſt ſubverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Catholic Faith, in the firſt and chief Article of it. The Doctor however
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:97237:29"/>was ſtill conſtant to his Doctrine; he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevered in his former <hi>I am ſure that I am in the right.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Shortly after came forth <hi>the judgment of a diſintereſted Perſon, concerning the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy between Dr.</hi> S—TH <hi>and Dr.</hi> SHER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LOCK. This Author ſtates the Doctrines of the Trinity, and the Incarnation or Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity of our Saviour, as they have been for many Ages held in the Catholic Church: and proves his explication of them, by a great number of inconteſtable Authorities, eſpecially of General Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils. He evinces by divers clear (both Theological and Philoſophical) Reaſons: that three infinite ſpiritual <hi>Subſtances,</hi> three eternal all-perfect <hi>Beings, Minds,</hi> or <hi>Spirits,</hi> are moſt certainly three <hi>Gods.</hi> He concludes that Dr. <hi>S—th</hi> and the <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> Heads are undoubtedly in the right, in cenſuring the Doctrine of three infinite all-perfect ſpiritual Subſtances, Spirits, Minds or Beings, as Tritheiſm; yet that Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> had no ill meaning; for he only propoſed to himſelf to defend the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Doctrines of the Trinity and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation, tho he unhappily miſtook in the explication of thoſe Doctrines. One may ſay this Book is perfectly well writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:97237:30"/>the Catholic Doctrine is truly ſtated and aſſerted by the very Authorities and Reaſons on which it has been ſo long and ſo generally received: and tho the Author is conſtrained by the evidence of the proofs which he alledges, to aſſent to the <hi>Oxford</hi>-Heads, and to Dr. <hi>S—th;</hi> yet he always ſpeaks of Dr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> not only with much tenderneſs, but with a great deal of reſpect and deference.</p>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> on the contrary, anſwers with ſo much virulence, as if the Author had done to him ſome perſonal irrepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or even mortal Injury: and with ſo much ſelf-conceit and confidence, as if himſelf had obtained the monopolies of Learning and good ſenſe.</p>
               <p>He intitles his anſwer to <hi>the diſintereſted,</hi> 
                  <q>The Doctrine of a <hi>real</hi> Trinity vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, in anſwer to <hi>a Socinian Pamphlet.</hi>
                  </q> As if it were Socinianiſm to oppoſe Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſm.</p>
               <p>He begins his Book with theſe words. <q>This Author calls himſelf <hi>a Presbyter of the Church of England:</hi> I pray God to preſerve the Church from ſuch Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, who eat her Bread, and betray her Faith.</q> His other <hi>Sippets</hi> are, <hi>Socinian Heretic, bantering Socinian,</hi> and ſuch like <hi>Sweets,</hi> with which this Doctor's diſhes are always enchaced.</p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:97237:30"/>
               <p>But to let thoſe matters paſs, in this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer he recites the Authorities and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons urged by <hi>the diſintereſted;</hi> and in a Paragraph or two beſtowed on <hi>each</hi> of them, he triumphs at laſt gloriouſly over <hi>all</hi> of them. But what is very ſurpriz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; tho he confutes all the Reaſons, and baffles all the Authorities in the whole Book, yet 'tis in this very Anſwer that he begins to bethink him, and retracts all his Heterodoxies; nay becomes altogether of the ſame mind with the Author againſt whom he writes. Let us hear what he ſays.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 12. <q>The Nominals (<hi>i. e.</hi> Dr. <hi>S—th</hi> and the <hi>Oxford</hi> Heads) and the <hi>Socinians</hi> differ in ſome <hi>forms of Speech,</hi> but there is no conſiderable difference in their <hi>Faith.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>P.</hi> 6. <q>Theſe Phraſes, three <hi>Minds,</hi> three <hi>Spirits,</hi> three <hi>Subſtances,</hi> ought to be uſed very cautiouſly, and not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great neceſſity.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>P.</hi> 14. <q>They are Expreſſions liable to a very heretical ſenſe, to Arianiſm and Tritheiſm.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>P.</hi> 30. <q>In the common acceptation of the word, <hi>the Divine Perſons are not three Subſtances;</hi> but <hi>one</hi> Subſtance actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and really ſubſiſting <hi>thrice.</hi>
                  </q> He meant to ſay, <hi>three manner of ways;</hi> ſubſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>thrice</hi> is nonſenſe.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:97237:31"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>P.</hi> 35. <q>The Trinity is one ſupream <hi>Being;</hi> this is the Doctrine of St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> the Schools and Fathers.</q> Can any one ſay Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> hath not given ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the <hi>Oxford</hi>-Heads, and Dr. <hi>S—th?</hi> Were <hi>F. Socinus, Smalcius, Crellius,</hi> and <hi>Ruarus</hi> to judg of this Doctrine, they would be content it ſhould be inſerted into their Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covian Catechiſm, they would embrace the Author as an abſolute Unitarian.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>P.</hi> 36. <q>Father, Son and Spirit are <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, one and the ſame <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance;</hi> they are <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the unity, of Sameneſs or <hi>Identity:</hi> This is true Catholick Doctrine, and the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the Nicene Fathers: And of all the <hi>Socinians,</hi> from <hi>F. Sacinus</hi> to Mr. <hi>T. F.</hi>
                  </q> But we ſhall hear by and by he will confeſs that alſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>P.</hi> 61. <q>Three infinite <hi>Perſons,</hi> each of which is <hi>Mind</hi> and <hi>Spirit,</hi> are but one and the ſame infinite and eternal Spirit.</q> Catholick again, and Unitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an all over: For when the Church ſays, each Divine Perſon is Mind and Spirit; the meaning is, the Divine Perſons are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal <hi>relative Properties,</hi> of the <hi>ſame</hi> infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Mind and Spirit: and being ſo, each of them indeed is Mind and Spirit, but not <hi>a</hi> Mind or <hi>a</hi> Spirit. Had Dr. <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock</hi>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:97237:31"/>but known this in time, he had never wrote againſt the Unitarians, nor fallen under the <hi>Oxford</hi>-Cenſure.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>P.</hi> 65. <q>The <hi>Socinians</hi> will grant that one Divinity is but one God: and the reaſon why they aſſert that <hi>one God is but one Perſon,</hi> is, becauſe they think it impoſſible the ſame <hi>undivided</hi> Divinity ſhould ſubſiſt <hi>diſtinctly</hi> in three Perſons. But then before they had charged the Faith of the Trinity with Tritheiſm, they ſhould have remembred, that the Perſons of the Trinity are not three <hi>ſuch</hi> Perſons as <hi>their</hi> one Perſon is, whom they call one God: and therefore tho three <hi>ſuch</hi> Perſons, three ſuch Minds, Spirits and Subſtances, as <hi>their</hi> one Perſon and one Spirit is, (who is the whole Divinity confined to one ſingle Perſon) would indeed be three Gods; yet three <hi>ſuch</hi> Perſons as the Catholic Church owns, who are all <hi>the ſame One Subſtance,</hi> are not three Gods.</q> The ſhort of this is, the Church doth not mean by three Perſons, what the <hi>Socinians</hi> mean; if ſhe did, they would rightly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe her of <hi>Tritheiſm;</hi> three ſuch Perſons as the <hi>Socinians</hi> oppoſe are indeed <hi>three Gods.</hi> He repeats the ſame thing, <hi>p.</hi> 67, in theſe words: <q>The three Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:97237:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <hi>as we have now explained them,</hi> are not three <hi>ſuch</hi> Perſons; as the <hi>Socinians</hi> muſt confeſs three Perſons muſt be who are three Gods.</q> Right, for you have now acknowledged that what you call <hi>three Perſons</hi> is indeed <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>one ſelf-ſame ſpiritual Subſtance,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of Indentity, one ſupream Being, one and the ſame infinite and eternal Spirit:</hi> which in all your former Books, was <hi>Nonſenſe</hi> and <hi>Hereſy,</hi> and <hi>not greater Nonſenſe than Hereſy;</hi> as they who pleaſe may ſee in the places I have quoted, and in above forty other places of your Writings. I ſhall tell you not only the <hi>Oxford</hi>-Heads, or Dr. <hi>S—th,</hi> but <hi>F. Socinus</hi> or <hi>T. F.</hi> would never have required you to ſay more than you now ſay: it was not the Trinity held by the Catholic Church, that <hi>Socinus</hi> or <hi>T. F.</hi> rejected; but only a Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of <hi>ſuch</hi> Divine Perſons, as are <hi>diſtinct</hi> Subſtances, Spirits and Minds, which (at length) you alſo expreſly diſown: but which too many in the Church, miſled by the dangerous unſcriptural terms, now ſo much contended for, <hi>did</hi> and <hi>do</hi> hold. There can never be a ſincere Peace, till thoſe terms are diſcarded. For tho after eight years Diſputation, a Doctor of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and a Dean has been hardly perſwad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:97237:32"/>out of the Hereſy of three Spirits, Minds or Subſtances: yet the continuance of theſe unſcriptural Terms, without an exact Explication of them in Sermons and Catechiſms, <hi>heathenizes</hi> all the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon People, nay and great numbers of not unlearned perſons.</p>
               <p>'Tis evident now I ſuppoſe to every bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, that the <hi>Diſintereſted</hi> was not concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to reply to ſuch an Anſwer as this. Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> indeed confuted moſt plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly all his Reaſons, and trampled upon his Authorities: but kindly granted him the Doctrine for which he contended.</p>
               <p>I was in hope therefore all the duſt and noiſe had been at an end; but Dr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> who has no mercy on a conquer'd Enemy, thought fit to make a new Onſet. He publiſht a Sermon, concerning <hi>the danger of corrupting the Faith by Philoſophy:</hi> in which with a great deal of bitterneſs, and many Invectives againſt the Unitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, he declares, that, <q>The Unitarian (and all other Hereſies) have their riſe and ſtrength from Philoſophy and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</q> He pretends that Religion muſt be learned, and taught only from Holy Scripture; not indeed from the meer Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or Phraſe of Holy Scripture, without allowance for Metaphors, and ſuch like
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:97237:33"/>Schemes of Speech; but from the obvious and natural ſenfe of the words of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; without preſuming to mollify or change in the leaſt, what ſeems to be the proper ſenſe of the words, on the account of any Oppoſition thereto by Reaſon or Philoſophy. He takes occaſion here to declame againſt Reaſon and Philoſophy, as moſt dangerous Deceits and Impoſtures, the true Originals and Cauſes of all Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies and Errors in Religion. His topicks of Argument for theſe things, are the ſame that have been always advanced by the maintainers of Tranſubſtantiation, &amp; other ſuch like Doctrines; which have been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected by the Proteſtant Churches, on the account that they are flatly contrary to Reaſon and Philoſophy. This Sermon had been out but a little time, when Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> publiſht <hi>Remarks</hi> on it. The Author of the <hi>Remarks,</hi> firſt makes an Abſtract or Summary of the Sermon; and then examins part by part, the ſaid Summa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry or Abſtract. He proves, that the uſe of Philoſophy and Reaſon is even neceſſary for the right underſtanding of Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or of any other Book or Speech what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever; and that 'tis by Reaſon, which is no other thing but <hi>common ſenſe,</hi> and by Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, which is nothing but <hi>experimental
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:97237:33"/>Knowledg,</hi> that we can judg when a Book (confeſt on all hands to be true and certain) ſpeaks figuratively and popularly, and when ſtrictly, grammatically and literally. In a word, 'tis by Reaſon and Philoſophy chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the true meaning and intention of any Book, which Book or Writing is grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be certainly true, can be found.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Remarks</hi> are ſo written, that Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> thinks fit to deny, that his Sermon is truly repreſented; he ſays in his <hi>Vindication of the Sermon,</hi> 
                  <q>The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the <hi>Remarks,</hi> gives the ſenſe of my Sermon in his own words, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly contrary to my meaning. —I who made the Sermon knew nothing of it but by mere gueſs, as it lays in his Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract. <bibl>
                        <hi>Vind. p.</hi> 4.</bibl>
                  </q> He adds again, at <hi>p.</hi> 28. <q>The Author of the <hi>Remarks</hi> has not oppoſed the Doctrine of my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon; but his own Chimeras and Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies.</q> In ſhort, the Doctor complains, that his whole Sermon is miſreported by the Author of the <hi>Remarks;</hi> and that it was not at all his Intention in the Sermon, to ſpeak againſt Philoſophy or Reaſon, but only againſt what <hi>ſome men call Philoſophy and Reaſon;</hi> and againſt <hi>vain pretences to Reaſon and Philoſophy,</hi> Vind. p. 5. He quotes two or three mincing paſſages of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:97237:34"/>his Sermon, which ſpeak not of philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy and Reaſon, but of <hi>Pretenders</hi> and <hi>Pretences</hi> to Reaſon and Philoſophy; and theſe two or three Paſſages he offers as the true and <hi>whole</hi> intention of his Sermon. But,</p>
               <p>It is certain, himſelf had other thoughts of the intention of his Sermon, when he publiſh'd it, and before he law it confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: for he gives it this Title, <hi>The danger of corrupting Religion by Philoſophy;</hi> not by <hi>Pretender,</hi> or <hi>Pretences to Philoſophy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis certain, alſo, that the Arguments he alledges are directed againſt Philoſophy it ſelf, and Reaſon it ſelf; as every one ſees in the Sermon, and in the Vindication of it. He has (for inſtance) this paſſage, laugh'd at by ſo many. <hi>If</hi> a. Contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>to fallible</hi> Senſe, <hi>be not a good objection againſt the truth of any thing; how comes</hi> a Contradiction <hi>to much more fallible</hi> Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>to be an unanſwerable objection?</hi> Vind. p. 14.</p>
               <p>Farther, when he is explaining his Text, he ſays. <q>
                     <hi>Beware, leſt any ſpoil you thro' Philoſophy and vain Deceit;</hi> that is, <hi>thro' the vain deceit of Philoſophy: Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy cheats men with a flattering but falſe appearance.</hi> It may unſettle weak minds, but cannot lay a ſure or ſolid
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:97237:34"/>foundation for Faith; it may cheat men out of their Faith, but, when that is done, can give nothing in the room of it. <bibl>
                        <hi>Serm. p.</hi> 2.</bibl>
                  </q> He has divers ſuch paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages, addreſſed directly againſt Reaſon and Philoſophy: but after the <hi>Remarks</hi> on thoſe paſſages came abroad, he thought (it ſhould ſeem) that, ſeeing what he had ſo haſtily ſaid could no ways be defended, his beſt way would be to deny that ever he ſaid or intended it. He thought, perhaps, it would be a leſs loſs of Reputation, if two or three prying malicious Fellows will read the Sermon again, and thereby diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver either that the Doctor had forgot him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, or would venture (in a ſtreight) on an apparent falſity; than to make himſelf contemptible to learned and diſcerning Men, by pertinacy in Opinions that had been ſo clearly refuted. I leave it to others to judg whether this were an exact Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation.</p>
               <p>But, I think, I had not mentioned this Sermon, or its Vindication, but that here again the Doctor calls in his Heterodoxies concerning the Trinity. He diſowns here the expreſſion <hi>three infinite Minds and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,</hi> as very inconvenient, and liable to an heretical Interpretation: it ought not to be uſed, he ſaith, in <hi>the abſolute;</hi> but only
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:97237:35"/>in <hi>a qualified</hi> and <hi>reſtrained Senſe.</hi> His words are, <hi>I freely acknowledg, that</hi> three infinite Minds and Spirits, <hi>is liable to a</hi> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Heretical <hi>and</hi> Tritheiſtic Senſe, <hi>if un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood</hi> abſolutely. <hi>Serm. p.</hi> 3. But this was never acknowledged till <hi>the Judgment by the Diſintereſted,</hi> and the <hi>Remarks,</hi> had extorted it from him.</p>
               <p>I come now to his third and <hi>laſt book of Retractations,</hi> his <hi>preſent ſtate of the Socinian Controverſy;</hi> which, as 'tis much larger than any of the reſt, ſo 'tis more expreſs and direct againſt the Hereſy of three infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite eternal Minds, Spirits, Beings, or Subſtances. 'Tis alſo written ſo much more calmly, than any former piece by the ſame hand; that I could ſcarce believe it was Doctor <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s. Abating a little grumbling of the gizard againſt Dr. <hi>S—th</hi> and the <hi>Oxford</hi> Heads, for former harſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and irreverence; and a ſmall aking of the teeth againſt the unpardonable <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> the Cauſers (or however the Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners) of all our Misfortunes: the book is wrote in a reaſonable and pacific manner; the only book of a great many, ſo written by this Author. I will preſent the Reader with the Doctrine of this remarkable and uſeful Book, under diſtinct heads; that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:97237:35"/>one may ſee he hath entirely chang'd his opinions, that were cenſured by the <hi>Oxford</hi> Heads, and refuted by the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> concerning God; what is <hi>the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition of God,</hi> and of what ſort is <hi>the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity?</hi> He anſwers;</p>
               <p>P. 25. <hi>This is the notion that</hi> all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind <hi>have of one God,</hi> one infinite eternal Being, or Nature.</p>
               <p>P. 35. God is an eternal infinite Mind. <hi>So</hi> all, <hi>as well Chriſtians as Philoſophers, hold.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>P. 49. <hi>What is</hi> the natural Notion <hi>we have of God? But</hi> one eternal Being, <hi>the cauſe of all other Beings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>P. 309. <hi>They (the Divine Perſons) are</hi> as perfectly One, as a created Mind is.</p>
               <p>P. 319. <hi>A Perichoreſis, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, or mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Inbeing of minds, can never make three compleat abſolute Minds to be eſſentially one.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>P. 343. Three <hi>(abſolute, whole, indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual)</hi> Divine Natures, is Tritheiſm.</p>
               <p>P. 371. <hi>The Divine Perſons</hi> cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly be called three infinite Minds or Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits. <hi>For Mind, as well as God, is not the name of their perſons; but of their nature, which is</hi> identically the ſame <hi>in all three.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:97237:36"/>
               <p>We ſee here, he propounds the Doctrine of the Church, and of the Unitarians, both Affirmatively and Negatively, and both ways makes it his own. In defining or deſcribing God, he ſaith, one God is <hi>one</hi> infinite <hi>BEING, one</hi> eternal and infinite <hi>MIND:</hi> And tho' we ſay three Divine <hi>Perſons,</hi> yet (whatever is thereby meant, and he will tell us by and by what is meant) they are <hi>as perfectly one MIND, as a created mind is one.</hi> Then Negatively he ſays, The Divine Perſons are not three Minds or Spirits: and as to what ſome ſay, and himſelf had often ſaid in former Books of the <hi>Perichoreſis,</hi> he now owns no mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al <hi>Inbeing</hi> of three Spirits or Minds, can ever make them to be one.</p>
               <p>In accounting for the nature of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <hi>Perſons,</hi> he ſpeaks the very language of <hi>the Diſintereſted,</hi> of the Author of the <hi>Remarks;</hi> and of <hi>the Agreement</hi> that was wrote in anſwer to Mr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> to my Lords the Biſhops of <hi>Sarum, Chicheſter, Worceſter,</hi> and to Monſieur <hi>de Luzanzy.</hi> His words are theſe.</p>
               <p>P. 256. <hi>We acknowledg one God, diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed</hi> only <hi>by theſe</hi> perſonal Properties, <hi>Paternity, Filiation, Proceſſion, as each of them has a compleat Hypoſtaſis,</hi> diſtinguiſh'd only by MODES <hi>of ſubſiſtence.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:97237:36"/>
               <p>P. 258. <hi>The Divine Nature ſubſiſts di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly in three; according to their diſtinct characters of</hi> Unbegotten, Begotten, <hi>and</hi> Procee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing. <hi>And theſe we call</hi> Perſons, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have</hi> ſome Analogy (or likeneſs) <hi>to individuals in created Beings; which, in an</hi> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>telligent <hi>nature, are called</hi> Perſons. P. 197. <hi>We muſt uſe ſuch words as we have; and</hi> qualify their ſenſe, <hi>as we can.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>P. 259. <hi>When we diſtinguiſh between</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon <hi>and</hi> Eſſence; <hi>and ſay there are</hi> three <hi>Perſons and</hi> one <hi>Eſſence: By one</hi> Eſſence, <hi>we mean one</hi> Divinity; <hi>by</hi> Perſons <hi>we mean the Divine Eſſence</hi> as <hi>unbegotten, and</hi> as <hi>communicated by</hi> Generation <hi>and</hi> Proceſſion.</p>
               <p>P. 280. <hi>Tho each Divine</hi> Perſon <hi>is the Divine</hi> Nature <hi>and</hi> Eſſence; <hi>yet three Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perſons are not three Natures or Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but</hi> three Relations in one ſingular ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Nature.</p>
               <p>P. 297. <hi>That one</hi> Nature <hi>is but one</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>and one Perſon but one Nature; that individual Natures and Perſons muſt always be multiplyed with each other, is the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Principle of all Hereſies, relating ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the Trinity or the Incarnation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sure this laſt effort was a very hard and grievous ſtrain to him; for 'twas the very principle that miſled him into the Hereſy of three ſpiritual infinite Subſtances, Minds
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:97237:37"/>and Beings. He took it for his foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that <hi>Perſons</hi> and intelligent Natures or <hi>Subſtances,</hi> are convertible, or are the ſame: and this error made him obſtinate in it, even after the <hi>Oxford</hi> Decree, that the Divine Perſons ye ſo many diſtinct ſpiritual Subſtances, diſtinct Spirits and Minds.</p>
               <p>Well, but let us put together this whole <hi>reformed Doctrine,</hi> about the Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. They are not diſtinct <hi>Beings, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, Subſtances, Minds,</hi> or <hi>Spirits;</hi> but only <hi>perſonal Properties,</hi> or <hi>diſtinct Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the ſame ſingular nature.</hi> Would you know <hi>the Myſtery</hi> more particularly, what you are to underſtand by perſonal <hi>Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> and diſtinct <hi>Relations,</hi> in the ſame ſingular Nature or Eſſence? The Doctor will not be difficult or reſerved in the matter; he anſwers. The <hi>Perſons,</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal <hi>Properties,</hi> or diſtinct <hi>Relations,</hi> are <hi>the Divine Eſſence</hi> (or Subſtance) <hi>unbegot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,</hi> and communicated by Generation and Proceſſion; that is, <hi>Begotten</hi> and <hi>Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> Do you except againſt it, or make doubt, that <hi>Relations,</hi> perſonal <hi>Properties,</hi> Unbegotten, Begotten, and Proceeding, are properly called <hi>Perſons,</hi> or may have the names of Father, Son, and Spirit? He will deliver you from your ſcruples; he wiſely
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:97237:37"/>minds you, that <hi>we muſt of neceſſity uſe ſuch words as we have; and regulate or qualifie their ſenſe, as well as we can.</hi> In two words, he ſaith: <hi>The Divine</hi> Perſons <hi>are ſo called, becauſe we muſt uſe ſuch words as we have; and becauſe they have</hi> ſome <hi>likeneſs to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the created Nature: but in truth they are only</hi> perſonal Properties, <hi>or</hi> diſtinct Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, <hi>of the ſame ſingular nature, namely, of the Divinity. Or if you had rather, they are the Divine Eſſence, or Divinity, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as</hi> Unbegotten, Begotten, <hi>and</hi> Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. This is a true and an exact Abridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his large Book. I will not think he has ſo little conſcience as to pretend; that the Unitarians have in their late Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſts oppoſed this Trinity: 'tis the account that themſelves give of it, and profeſs to believe; in that part of <hi>the Agreement,</hi> which is in anſwer to my Lords the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of <hi>Worceſter</hi> and <hi>Chicheſter.</hi> 'Tis the account alſo given by Dr. <hi>S—th,</hi> in his <hi>Animadverſions,</hi> and his <hi>Tritheiſm charged;</hi> by the <hi>Diſintereſted,</hi> by the Biſhops of <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter</hi> and of <hi>Sarum.</hi> In eight years time, this fierce Oppoſer of the Unitarians has (with much to do) learned, that the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity is not three <hi>Minds, Spirits,</hi> or <hi>Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> but three internal <hi>Relations,</hi> three per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal <hi>Properties</hi> of the Divinity: In eight
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:97237:38"/>more, it may be, he will underſtand, that thoſe are good Catholics, and orthodox Chriſtians, who reject no other Trinity, but of diſtinct <hi>Subſtances, Spirits,</hi> or <hi>Minds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We are all agreed in the Faith it ſelf; and even as to the ordinary terms, the more learned <hi>Trinitarians</hi> wiſh, as the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitarians</hi> do, that they were aboliſht: but as to ſome other leſs uſual terms, that oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur in the debating theſe queſtions, there is ſome diſagreement among Divines; I take notice that, as to theſe, Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> is always on the worſe ſide, and for the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker Reaſons.</p>
               <p>For Inſtances. 'Tis a queſtion, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we may not ſay <hi>three Divine Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> as well as <hi>three Perſons?</hi> They that put the queſtion, or that ſo ſpeak, grant that in very deed there is but <hi>one</hi> Divine Subſtance, in the <hi>abſolute</hi> ſenſe of the word: yet may we not ſay (with Sr. <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary</hi>) <hi>three</hi> Subſtances, in a reſtrained limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and <hi>relative ſenſe?</hi> That is, meaning thereby, the one real Divine Subſtance, conſidered in its diſtinct: <hi>Relations</hi> or <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties:</hi> for hereby the Subſtance, tho 'tis not multiply'd, yet 'tis <hi>thrice</hi> numbred; and in that reſpect, it ſhould ſeem, may be, called three <hi>relative</hi> Subſtances. This is a very ſlight Reaſoning, and never miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:97237:38"/>any body but St. <hi>Hilary.</hi> For men ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſay THREE, on the account that a thing is conſidered <hi>three manner of ways;</hi> with three <hi>Modes,</hi> three <hi>Properties,</hi> or three <hi>Relations.</hi> Why therefore ſhould we introduce ſuch an improper, as well as dangerous form of ſpeaking concerning God: a form of ſpeaking that in its natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and immediate ſenſe, deſtroys the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Unity; and introduces, by their own confeſſion, three Gods? Notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> is pleaſed to approve of that form; he ſaith,</p>
               <p>P. 379. <hi>We muſt not ſay</hi> three Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <hi>in the Trinity, for fear of ſaying</hi> three Gods. <hi>Yet we muſt own that each Divine Perſon is true and perfect ſubſtance; and three in ſubſtance are</hi> three Subſtances: <hi>not indeed three</hi> abſolute, <hi>but three</hi> relative <hi>Subſtances. —In the Trinity there is</hi> one <hi>abſolute, and</hi> three relative <hi>Subſtances.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>P. 287. <hi>An</hi> abſolute <hi>Subſtance is one entire, perfect, individual Whole:</hi> Relative <hi>Subſtances are internal ſubſiſting</hi> Relations, <hi>in the ſame one whole individual ſubſtance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>meaning</hi> is Orthodox; the <hi>words</hi> Heterodox, and Phantaſtical. He grants that to affirm three Divine Subſtances, is to affirm three Gods: but then, meaning by Subſtances, <hi>what no body means,</hi> the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:97237:39"/>ſame one abſolute individual Subſtance numbred three times, or numbred with its three <hi>Properties,</hi> or Relations, we may affirm three Divine <hi>relative</hi> Subſtances.</p>
               <p>Again. Thoſe that grant, it muſt not be ſaid in any ſenſe whatſoever, that there are <hi>three</hi> Divine Subſtances; yet they make it a queſtion, Whether the one only Divine Subſtance is one <hi>numerical</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and one <hi>ſingular</hi> Subſtance? They own the Divine Subſtance is really but one, <hi>identically</hi> one; 'tis one <hi>ſelf-ſame</hi> Subſtance, not two or three, in whatſoever ſenſe. For all that, they are not willing to ſay; the ſubſtance of God is <hi>numerically one,</hi> is one <hi>numerical,</hi> or one <hi>ſolitary,</hi> or <hi>ſingular</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance: their wiſe Reaſon is this. Tho' the Divine Subſtance is one <hi>in Nature,</hi> and <hi>in the thing numbred,</hi> as the School-Doctors, ſpeak; yet being <hi>thrice numbred,</hi> for it is numbred diſtinctly to (or <hi>with</hi>) its three <hi>Properties,</hi> or <hi>Relations:</hi> therefore we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it to be <hi>numerically</hi> one; tho 'tis <hi>really, naturally,</hi> and <hi>identically</hi> one. Now we grant to theſe Anti-Grammarians, that the thing they intend, is true: but they ſhould not deny propoſitions, that are true <hi>in their Grammatical and immediate Senſe;</hi> becauſe they are not true <hi>in a ſenſe, that no man ever was ſo wild as to impoſe it
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:97237:39"/>upon them.</hi> 'Tis ſomething worſe than trifling, to deny orthodox and <hi>neceſſary</hi> Propoſitions, on a pretence that mad men may take them in a ſenſe contrary to their direct, immediate and conſtant meaning. When we ſay, the divine (or any <hi>other</hi>) Subſtance is numerically one; or is one <hi>nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merical,</hi> one <hi>ſingular,</hi> one <hi>ſolitary</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance: every body knows that the words ſolitary, ſingular and numerical, are uſed only in oppoſition to <hi>plural, more,</hi> or <hi>many;</hi> ſo that one <hi>ſolitary, ſingular,</hi> or <hi>numerically one</hi> Subſtance, is intended only as a denial of this heretical Propoſition, <hi>three Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances.</hi> If the reaſon given by Dr. <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock,</hi> and ſome few others, why they will not ſay, one <hi>ſingular,</hi> or <hi>ſolitary,</hi> or <hi>numerically one</hi> Subſtance, were good; they muſt never ſay one <hi>numerical,</hi> one ſolitary or ſingular <hi>Earth</hi> or <hi>Sun,</hi> or other body or thing whatſoever. Nay, they muſt not dare to ſay, <hi>numerically one</hi> GOD, one <hi>ſingular</hi> or <hi>ſolitary</hi> GOD; which yet are forms, that (I preſume) they will own as orthodox, nay as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary. There is no <hi>thing</hi> or <hi>being</hi> whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, but muſt be at leaſt <hi>thrice numbred;</hi> namely to the three Properties of every Being, <hi>Verum, bonum unum:</hi> therefore if
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:97237:40"/>we muſt not ſay, one <hi>numerical,</hi> or one <hi>ſingular</hi> or <hi>ſolitary</hi> Divine Subſtance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this Subſtance is thrice numbred, <hi>viz.</hi> with or <hi>to</hi> its three <hi>Relations</hi> or <hi>Properties;</hi> neither may we ſay one nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical, or one ſolitary or ſingular <hi>Earth,</hi> or <hi>Sun,</hi> becauſe they are <hi>thrice numbred,</hi> are diſtinctly numbred to the three Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Verum, bonum, unum.</hi> But this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent niceneſs, Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> every where takes up, and contends for it, as an <hi>important</hi> truth: unleſs we exclude the terms <hi>ſolitary, ſingular</hi> and <hi>numerical,</hi> he is poſitive that we ſhall loſe the three Divine Perſons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>P.</hi> 195. <q>The <hi>ſingularity</hi> of the Divine Subſtance is a <hi>Sabellian</hi> Notion, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys the faith of a <hi>real</hi> Trinity.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>P.</hi> 213. <q>An <hi>individual</hi> Subſtance; but not one <hi>ſolitary,</hi> or <hi>ſingular</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>P.</hi> 246. <q>The Unity of the Divine Subſtance or <hi>Nature</hi> is <hi>not an unity of number,</hi> but <hi>of ſameneſs,</hi> and identity.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>P.</hi> 249. <q>'Tis not a <hi>ſingular</hi> Nature or Subſtance, with <hi>the ſingularity of ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude,</hi> but of <hi>identity</hi> or ſameneſs.</q>
               </p>
               <p>I imagine Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s beſt Friends will not deny, 'tis an odd melancholy hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:97237:40"/>of his, to eſpouſe and affect: Terms and Phraſes, that have been rejected by all Learned Men, as improper, dangerous, and tending to Tritheiſm; merely that he may amuſe Novices in theſe Queſtions, and may afterward explain his Riddles, to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration of the weak or unlearned, and the ſleight of the learned and diſcerning.</p>
               <p>He concludes his Book, with an Addreſs to the Unitarians, to this effect. <q>They were not beſt to concern themſelves, with him, or againſt his Book; for if they do, they ſhall certainly be called to account for it <hi>in this World,</hi> as well as in the World to come.</q> I take this to be another melancholy Fit: for the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox will but laugh at the threatnings of a Man under publick Cenſure, for the very worſt Heterodoxy. What! three <hi>relative</hi> subſtances, call to account honeſt, orthodox <hi>one abſolute</hi> Subſtance? Believe me, Doctor, they deſpiſe the menace. They ſend you word, <hi>Phyſitian heal thy ſelf.</hi> Mr. Informer, purge your own Books, even this <hi>laſt,</hi> of the many Hete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodoxies in it. As,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 191. <q>The Son is nothing elſe but the whole, entire, immediate
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:97237:41"/>participation of the Father's Subſtance; and therefore is as perfectly one with the Father, as the Father is one.</q> 'Tis <hi>Sabellian.</hi> The Son is not ſo one with the Father, as the Father is one; for the Father is <hi>numerically one,</hi> as all confeſs: but Father and Son are <hi>numerically two,</hi> with all but <hi>Sabellians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>P.</hi> 198. <q>Each of them (Father, Son and Spirit) is perfect God; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>an</hi> infinite <hi>Mind,</hi> and <hi>an</hi> infinite Spirit</q>. 'Tis <hi>Tritheiſm:</hi> For if each of the Divine Perſons is <hi>an</hi> infinite Mind, or <hi>an</hi> infinite Spirit; then there are <hi>three</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite <hi>Minds</hi> and Spirits: which is the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy you have been retracting throughout this whole Book. I ſupooſe however, he meant to ſay, each Divine Perſon is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Mind and Spirit; which is Catholic, and Unitarian.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>P.</hi> 247. <q>To have aſſerted one <hi>ſingular</hi> Divine Subſtance, which is but <hi>one in number,</hi> had given up the cauſe to the Sabellians.</q> One <hi>ſingular</hi> Divine Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and <hi>one in number,</hi> is the Language of the Catholic Church, and is refuſed by none but <hi>Arians</hi> and <hi>Tritheiſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>P</hi> 369. <q>The name <hi>God</hi> doth not ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally, abſolutely, and immediately
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:97237:41"/>belong to the Son or Spirit; but <hi>only relatively.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>P.</hi> 373. <q>Only the Father is <hi>abſolutely</hi> and <hi>ſimply</hi> God.</q> 'Tis <hi>abſolute</hi> Hereſy. Taking <hi>Father, Son</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal ſenfe; the Son and Spirit are no leſs <hi>abſolutely</hi> and <hi>ſimply</hi> GOD than the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is. When the Unitarians ſay, <hi>only the Father is God in the abſolute ſenſe;</hi> they do not take the word Father <hi>perſonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly:</hi> but by <hi>Father</hi> they mean the Deity. Father, Son and Spirit, <hi>as Perſons of the Deity</hi> (taking <hi>Perſons</hi> in the Eccleſiaſtical ſenſe, or ſenſe of the Church) are <hi>equally God:</hi> neither is <hi>afore</hi> or <hi>after</hi> other, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>greater</hi> or <hi>leſs</hi> than the other, as <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius</hi> rightly teaches.</p>
               <p>In ſhort, this perpetual Litigant under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands not well, either the Doctrine of the Church, or the Party he oppoſes; theſe are not Queſtions, in which he might concern himſelf: they require an attention and ſubtilty of thought, which either he ſeems not to have had, or to have loſt. He has concerned himſelf in the ſuppoſed Controverſy between the Church and the <hi>Socinians,</hi> with like prudence, dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terity and ſucceſs, as the <hi>preſent</hi> Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop, of <hi>Paris</hi> has intermedled between
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:97237:42"/>the <hi>Janſeniſts</hi> and <hi>Moliniſts.</hi> The Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop publiſhed an Ordinance, againſt a Book entituled, <hi>An Expoſition of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholic Faith, touching Grace and Predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</hi> Father <hi>Queſnel,</hi> a Prieſt of the Oratory, and Mr, <hi>du Guè,</hi> a Learned Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but who has laid aſide the habit, have ſeverally written upon this Ordinance. They agree that what is propoſed <hi>as Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholic Doctrine</hi> in the <hi>ſecond</hi> Part of the Archbiſhop's Ordinance, is really the ſame with what is cenſured in the <hi>firſt</hi> Part <hi>as the Hereſy of the Janſeniſts:</hi> but in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther point theſe two Criticks differ. For Mr. <hi>du Guè</hi> thinks the Archbiſhop may be pardoned the Errors in the firſt Part, in conſideration of his ſecond Part: but Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Queſnel</hi> doth not approve this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence of Mr. <hi>du Guè;</hi> he maintains that the Archbiſhop cannot make ſatisfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion but only by <hi>a Recantation.</hi> 'Tis well for Dr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> that he dos not write <hi>among</hi> or <hi>to</hi> the Wits of <hi>France:</hi> for his Books concerning theſe Queſtions, in truth are nothing but <hi>heaps of Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions.</hi> A Perſon well verſed in the Controverſy may ſpell out his meaning, and find what is the Writer's aim; but he muſt pardon a thouſand Impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieties
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:97237:42"/>and Blunders, and as many Contradictions, ſome of them in the very ſtreſs, turn, or (as they ſpeak) nicety of the Controverſy.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
